<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The politicks of the French King, Lewis the XIV. discovered with respect to Rome. Emperour, and princes of the Empire. Spain. England. United Provinces. Northern princes. Suisse cantons: and of Savoy. With a short account of his religion. Translated from the French. Licensed according to order.</title>
            <title>Aprit de la France et les maximes de Louis XIV découvertes  ̀l'Europe. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90805</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2770A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229739</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895510</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895510</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152962</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90805)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152962)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2337:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The politicks of the French King, Lewis the XIV. discovered with respect to Rome. Emperour, and princes of the Empire. Spain. England. United Provinces. Northern princes. Suisse cantons: and of Savoy. With a short account of his religion. Translated from the French. Licensed according to order.</title>
                  <title>Aprit de la France et les maximes de Louis XIV découvertes  ̀l'Europe. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: L'esprit de la France et les maximes de Louis XIV découvertes à l'Europe.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>A different translation from Wing P3246, P3249, S4991, and S4991A.</note>
                  <note>ICN title page torn affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library, Chicago, Illinois.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152962:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE POLITICKS OF THE French KING, <hi>LEWIS</hi> the XIV.</p>
            <p>DISCOVERED: With Reſpect to
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Emperour,</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Empire.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Spain.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>United Provinces.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Northern Princes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Suiſſe Cantons:</hi> And of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With a ſhort Account of His RELIGION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated from the</hi> French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:152962:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152962:2"/>
            <head>THE Policy of France, And the MAXIMS of <hi>LEWIS</hi> the XIV. Diſcovered to all EUROPE.</head>
            <p>IT is not Birth which chiefly diſtinguiſhes Princes from other Men, but their Parts and Abilities: How many of them find we in Hiſtory; who having but an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſhare of them, make no other figure, but to fill up Genealogy; and whoſe Birth-days, and the days of their Death, are the only two which make any noiſe in the World. 'Tis according as this Spirit or Genius is diſpoſed in a Soveraign, that he acts for the good and welfare, or for the misfortune and undoing of his People. <hi>Wo to thee O Land,</hi> ſaith the Wiſe Man, <hi>when thy King is a Child, and thy Princes eat in the Morning: Bleſſed art thou, O Land,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152962:3"/>when thy King is the Son of Nobles, and thy Princes eat in due ſeaſon for Strength, and not for Drunkenneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation were happy under <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> but <hi>Rehoboam</hi> ſpoke to them in this manner, <hi>My little Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhall be thicker than my Fathers Loyns; for whereas my Father put an heavy Yoak upon you, I will put more to your Yoak: My Father chaſtiſed you with Whips, but I will chaſtiſe you with Scorpions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> was called <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> Father of the People of <hi>Rome;</hi> but <hi>Nero</hi> their Hangman. <hi>Philip</hi> II. was born of a wiſe Father, who Reigned with general applauſe; but yet he was a Blood-thirſty Man, who ſpared not his own Blood, and ſquandred away what <hi>Charles</hi> V. had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved with ſo much Glory and Prudence. <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt was the Idol of the <hi>French,</hi> and Darling of the Nobility; he acquired the Title of a mild, gentle Prince in peace, Victorious in War, the Father and Reſtorer of Learning and liberal Arts; but <hi>Charles</hi> IX. that of Murtherer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> IV. was ſurnamed the Great, by reaſon of his great Actions, he was the Darling and Father of his People, and his beneficent ſweet diſpoſition ſeem'd to promiſe a happy Reign, if a curſed Hand had not put a ſtop to the courſe of his Life. <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. was ſurnamed the Juſt, grounded without doubt upon the Goſpel, which aſſures us, <hi>That bleſſed are the poor in Spirit, and that theirs is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven.</hi> It was rather <hi>Richlieu</hi>'s Spirit that reigned than his.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. did not diſcover his Inclinations whilſt he was under the Tuition of his Mother and <hi>Mazarines</hi> laſh, but ſo ſoon as ever this latter was dead, he ſhewed what he was.</p>
            <p>His Flatterers in imitation of his Grand father gave him the Name of <hi>Great,</hi> although he had not as yet deſerved it. 'Tis true indeed, He is Great, as to his Ambition, a great
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152962:3"/>Uſurper of the Territories of his Neighbour, a great Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the Holy See, to the Pope, and a great Perſecutor of the Hugonots, His Reign is full of nothing but great Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polyes, and his <hi>Louis d'ors</hi> are the only <hi>paſſe par touts,</hi> or Keys that open the Gates to his Conqueſts. He was born Armed, and his firſt nouriſhment was the Blood of his Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which he drew himſelf, that ambitious Spirit he is poſſeſt withall, would willingly ſacrifice a good part of his Subjects to his Paſſion and Greatneſs: Wo be to thee O Land that groans under the burthen of ſuch a Prince! Wo to that People enſlaved under his Dominion! Under the Reign of <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Illuſtrious, the <hi>Jews</hi> often cryed to God, that he would deliver them out of the hand of their Oppreſſor: Why may not the <hi>French</hi> put up the like Petition; nay, and all <hi>Europe</hi> beſides to be delivered out of the hands of that Uſurper. <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great thought he already held in his hand the Scepter of the Monarchy of all <hi>Europe,</hi> when <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna</hi> was beſieged; yea, he thought it within two hairs breadth of its deſtruction, which he ſuppoſed inevitable, grounded upon the Propheſies of <hi>Drabitius;</hi> but perceiving this way ſtopt up, he betakes himſelf to his firſt Errors and former Road, he waits with great impatience to ſee what the Snares which he lay'd at the time of the Queen of <hi>Spains</hi> Marriage, will produce: Man purpoſes, but God diſpoſeth.</p>
            <p>Time impairs the Mind as well as the Body, and Princes are oftentimes fain to let their Succeſſors do what they were not able to do themſelves, and ſo much the more, becauſe that ſame Divine Providence, on which Princes depend as well as the reſt of Mankind, doth not mete here below by the meaſure of their Ambition: Ambitious Men build Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the Air, and by their good will would poſſeſs the whole Earth beſide. This itch reigns at this day in <hi>France,</hi> and this is it which quite takes up the mind of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152962:4"/>as we ſhall ſee by the ſequel, and the courſe he takes to accompliſh his Deſigns.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Policy of <hi>France,</hi> and its Maxims in reſpect of all <hi>Europe</hi> in general.</head>
               <p>HEretofore Men accuſed <hi>Spain</hi> for aſpiring to an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Monarchy: If it was ſo, I ſuppoſe <hi>Philip</hi> II. begun to loſe this hope, when he perceiv'd the Sea and Winds op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his deſigns, and that the <hi>Armada,</hi> which he called In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible, (on Board of which he thought to have brought into <hi>Spain</hi> the <hi>Britiſh Iſles,</hi> &amp;c.) came to nothing, and that his choiceſt Troops who were embarqued therein, ſerved only to fight againſt the Waves, and feed the Fiſhes of the Sea; moreover, when he ſaw, that during the whole War of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> (a ſmall handful of People whom he called <hi>Gueux</hi> or Beggers, in deriſion) were alwayes able to hold up their Head againſt him, nay, and to beat him in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Encounters, until ſuch time as in the Year 1609, he was fain to cry Quarter, make a Truce with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> and acknowledge them for Free States.</p>
               <p>This was a very bitter Pill, and would ſcarce go down with a Prince who was ſo highly ambitious: But it behoved him to ſwallow it, and it wrought ſo ſtrongly upon him, that he loſt Seven Provinces at a clap by it, and part of the <hi>Indies:</hi> Inſomuch, That this longing deſire after the Univerſe began to abate by reaſon of his Age which had already loſt the firſt heat of Youth, and by reaſon of the bad ſucceſs of all his Enterprizes. <hi>Philip</hi> III. was as little fortunate as he, and <hi>Philip</hi> IV. had great diſappointments towards <hi>France</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152962:4"/>the <hi>Low Countreyes</hi> and was very glad by clapping up a Peace to acknowledge thoſe who had been his Subjects for a Free and Soveraign Commonwealth, holding of none but God Almighty. <hi>Charles</hi> XI. Reigning at preſent is a good Prince, who loves his eaſe, and would willingly quit all the Claims and Titles of his Anceſtors to an Univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy for a Son and Heir to the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> to ſucceed him. <hi>Malherbe</hi> told us long ſince, that if it were true, that <hi>Spain</hi> aſpir'd to an Univerſal Monarchy, he would adviſe his King to beg of God to prolong the World as much as he can. This Malady ceaſing in <hi>Spain,</hi> hath paſſed into <hi>France;</hi> but <hi>France</hi> being wiſer doth not graſp ſo much, and her King's Ambition is only confined to <hi>Europe,</hi> a wiſh worthy of ſuch a great Prince; and who, if we conſider him aright, could ſcarce demand leſs; his Neighbours ought narrowly to watch his water; for certain it is, <hi>France</hi> cannot aggran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize her ſelf without encroaching upon her neareſt Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; as ſhe doth really every day already. When the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> made broad ſigns of her deſign upon the Univerſe; all the Princes of Chriſtendom roſe up againſt her, and entered into an Aſſociation to prevent her. <hi>Charles</hi> V. after the Battel of <hi>Pavia,</hi> where <hi>Francis</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoner; thought himſelf above all, but he found bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs enough. The Pope, King of <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Venetians,</hi> the Grand Duke of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> the <hi>Swiſſe</hi> made a League againſt him, to hinder this Emperour from bringing <hi>France,</hi> and conſequently the reſt of <hi>Italy</hi> under his ſubjection. It was not for any kindneſs the Pope and King of <hi>England</hi> bore King <hi>Francis,</hi> that they combin'd together to relieve him, but becauſe <hi>Charles</hi> V. became ſo great, that he would by his good Will have made himſelf Maſter of the World. Now at preſent, foraſmuch as this Itch is paſt into <hi>France,</hi> All Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> for ſome time have run counter to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152962:5"/>whatſoever their Anceſtors did in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> V, and <hi>Philip</hi> II. and inſtead of oppoſing they have abetted and concurr'd with the deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> ſome out of baſe compliance, others out of fear. There are none but the Princes of <hi>Naſſau</hi> alone who have alwayes been fatal to whoſoever had a mind to aſpire to this ſublime Monarchy of the Univerſe: Do not Men admire with me the wretched Policy of ſeveral Princes and States in the World, who look on with their Armes a croſs, and behold the <hi>French</hi> King to advance ſo faſt, and take <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> a City of ſuch grand Importance to <hi>Europe;</hi> only the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> preſented himſelf upon the breach with the <hi>Low Countreys</hi> but who not being in a capacity to do any thing by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, was forced to retreat: The <hi>French</hi> King would never have taken it, had <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>States,</hi> withſtood it, he hath no cauſe to brag of it; it is a truth all the World knows but too well; he was ſo cunning to get the King of Great <hi>Britain</hi> on his ſide, that he conſented to take what was not his own, and to baffle the reſt by illuſory promiſes of an Univerſal Peace, after the taking in of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> which they ſuffered him to do; and this groſs valiant Captain (of a Trencher-man) the Marqueſs of <hi>Grana,</hi> Governour of the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> who was not promoted to this place, but upon his demonſtrating the means of being able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this moſt Important place to the Court of <hi>Spain;</hi> a place, I ſay, ſo neceſſary to <hi>Spain</hi> for the preſervation of the <hi>Low Countreys</hi> by the aſſiſtance of <hi>Germany;</hi> and albeit, he ſhould have minded nothing elſe, but the preſervation of that ſame City, his own Honour, as well as Duty to, and intereſt of his King his Maſter, being all engaged therein: Inſtead of doing which, this Fat-gut put into it only a piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Garriſon of Twelve, or Fifteen Hundred Men, inſtead of Four Thouſand, and was wholly taken up in fortifying
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152962:5"/>the City of <hi>Namur</hi> with his Regiments, and ſome other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which were Cities <hi>on the boundaries</hi> which <hi>France</hi> would not have dared ſo much as to touch: Would you not ſwear ſuch a Fellow conſpir'd to aggrandize <hi>France,</hi> and concurr'd with the Deſigns of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. When the King in 1667 would have undertaken the Conqueſt of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands, England, Swedeland,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> aſſociated together by the Triple League, forced him ſoon to quit his hold; they obliged him to re-procure, and make a Peace with <hi>Spain;</hi> and to reſtore to it, ſome part of what he had uſurped and taken away. It would have been juſt ſo, if the Neighbouring Princes had done the ſame at ſuch time as he attacked <hi>Luxemburg: Reſiſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and he will fly from you:</hi> But <hi>France</hi> cunning and ſubtle had ſufficiently tryed how prejudicial this League was to her; ſhe could never be at reſt till ſhe had pluckt this Thorn out of her Foot; and ſo ſoon as ever the term was expired, ſhe could not be ſatisfied till ſhe had found out a way to hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wink <hi>England,</hi> and ſo got her diſingaged from the Tripple-knot. The Dutcheſs of <hi>Portſmouth</hi> like another <hi>Dalilah</hi> came over out of <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> to lull aſleep the <hi>Sampſon</hi> of this Kingdom: <hi>France</hi> found out the way to act, and ſpeak ſo fair, that ſhe hook't in <hi>Dunkirk</hi> by Promiſes and Money, at the beginning of the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> II, King of <hi>Great Britain:</hi> A Town of ſo great Conſequence to <hi>England,</hi> in as much as it affords a good entrance into <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardy,</hi> and <hi>Flanders.</hi> 'Tis no new thing for <hi>France</hi> to be troubled with this itching mind to ſieze on the places of her Neighbours, and to enlarge her Dominion from one end of <hi>Europe</hi> to the other. The Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> told us hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that Princes commanded People; but that Self-Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt commanded Princes. (Without queſtion he would have added ſomething elſe had he lived in this Age,) and eſpecially
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152962:6"/>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. We may ſee Examples of it, day by day, and to ſecure his Ambition, all times and ſeaſons are good for him; in Peace, in War, in Ceſſation of Arms. Intereſt is the evil Angel hath ſo long reigned through <hi>France,</hi> we are taught out of Hiſtory, how <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Bulloign</hi> having a mind to take a Journey for the Conqueſt of the <hi>Holy Land;</hi> and coming ſhort of Money to put himſelf in a capacity to do it, ſold many of his Cities and Lands; amongſt others, the City of <hi>Metz</hi> with the Country adjoyning, which its own Citizens and Inhabitants purchaſed of him for the Sum of an Hundred Thouſand Crowns. They enjoyed this their purchaſe till the Year of our Lord 1551, in which <hi>Charles</hi> V. did ſo evilly intreat the Proteſtants of <hi>Germany. Henry</hi> II. King of <hi>France,</hi> under a pretence, ſeemed forward to ſend Relief to the ſaid Proteſtants of <hi>Germany:</hi> In effect, he diſpatched the Conſtable of <hi>Monmorency</hi> with Four Thouſand Men, in all probability for this Expedition; but it was quite and clean for another deſign, as the ſequel will make appear: He demanded paſſage of the City of <hi>Metz;</hi> who were for the moſt part of the ſame Religion with thoſe who were moleſted in <hi>Germany;</hi> between whom, and the Emperour, there was no good underſtanding: They gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the King with abundance of joy, whatſoever he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them in reference to his Troops paſſage; and in teſtimony of their good will, they cauſed Tables to be ſet up in the Streets, to make the Soldiers eat and drink on their paſſage, with huge demonſtration of Friendſhip and Rejoycing. But alas! Their Laughter was ſoon changed into Weeping; ſo ſoon as ever the Conſtable (who was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Magiſtrates with all Tokens of Honour and Benevolence) had entered the City, he feigned himſelf to have a fit of the Gout, and to feel intolerable pains; he declared his great deſire to have his Will made, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152962:6"/>what might befal him, in the War he was about to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence; and intreated the Magiſtrates of the City, and all the Nobility that they would aſſiſt as Witneſſes of it. In the mean time he had given order to two Colonels to ſieze, one of them upon the Gate by which the Troops entered, and the other on that, by which they went out. To the firſt, He gave order to cauſe part of the Army, which was ſtill without to advance; and to the other, to bid thoſe who were already gone out to enter in again: Now the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeeing the Magiſtrates and chief Nobility round his Bed, expecting his Orders; up ſtarts he like a Lyon enraged, and ſheathed his Ponyard in the Mayors Breaſt, and at the Signal given, his Guards ruſht in, and Aſſaſſinated all the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity they met with in his Chamber; whereupon the Army that had entered the City at the ſame time, cryed up and down the City, The Town is won: It was plundred, and ſubdued to the Bloody Dominion of the King, and of an Allie as it was, ſoon became a Subject. This was the Bloody Conqueſt of <hi>Henry</hi> II. And there is your <hi>French</hi> Policy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. not knowing how to get poſſeſſion of <hi>Lorain,</hi> by the Advice and Counſel of that moſt Subtle and Crafty Polititian Cardinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> comes to <hi>Lions</hi> with an Army under pretence of ſome deſign againſt <hi>Savoy.</hi> The <hi>Cardinal</hi> gave notice beforehand to Duke <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> that he ſhould make his perſonal appearance before the King, to pay him his reſpects, and aſſure him by word of mouth of his good intentions towards his Perſon. This Duke thinking no harm, ſuffered himſelf to be perſwaded to it in earneſt, departs from <hi>Nancy</hi> to ſalute the King at the head of his Troops: After he had complemented him, thinking he might return home again, he found it to be a Lions Den, arreſted he was upon pretence of ſome old claims. His
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152962:7"/>Eminence at that time performing the Office of Mediator, propounded that to make his peace with the King, and that he might enjoy his Liberty, to put into the Kings hands <hi>Nancy</hi> his chief City, and the Key of his Dutchy: Thus far he muſt go to be freed from his Arreſt: Well <hi>Nancy</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up, the King entered into it like a Conquerour with his Army at his heels: Obſerve the Policy of <hi>France</hi> in this particular.</p>
               <p>The demoliſhing of the Caſtle at <hi>Orange</hi> is juſt ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trick, ſhews their temper, for upon ſome little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that aroſe between the two Princeſſes, Royal, and Dowager, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. King of <hi>France,</hi> as uſually he doth, would intermeddle with it, and that he might make them agree, and that the young Prince (then under Age) avoid the Expences of maintaining a Garriſon there; he cauſed the Baſtions of the Caſtle to be pull'd down, and left nothing but the Dungeon, which together with the Town he could take at pleaſure, as ſince he hath done. What the ſame King did at <hi>Strasburg</hi> is much the ſame: This City look't upon its ſelf ſecure after the Treaty at <hi>Nemegen,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the powerful Letters the King writ to them time after time, after the aſſurances his Reſident then in the City gave them, that his Maſter deſired nothing more than to live in a fair correſpondence with the Emperour, and with the Cities of the Empire; laſt of all by the ſuits and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of the ſame Reſident, a Traitor was Elected Burgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, who did nothing but by the Council of <hi>France.</hi> The Magiſtracy and Citizens thus lull'd aſleep by all theſe fair promiſes and proteſtations, diſmiſt the <hi>Swiſſes</hi> their Guards; but they were no ſooner without doors, but Mr. <hi>Louvois</hi> with a puiſſant Army began to inveſt their City; obliges them to ſurrender on what conditions ſoever he thought fit to preſcribe them; even at this preſent they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152962:7"/>make no Conſcience to violate thoſe ſorry Articles which were granted to them, and to miſuſe them like Slaves, as he does all the reſt of his Subjects. Take notice of your Humour of <hi>France,</hi> which is always reſtleſs.</p>
               <p>After the peace at <hi>Nemeghen,</hi> how many Cities and Towns hath he taken in <hi>Flanders?</hi> How many of them hath he burnt and pull'd down to the Ground, to occaſion the peoples revolt, to cauſe them to rely wholly upon him to defend them from utter ruine, and to get free from all thoſe great Contributions wherewith he loads and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes them. Take notice of the <hi>French</hi> Policy.</p>
               <p>After the <hi>Pyrennean</hi> Treaty, which was but juſt ſigned, whereof this preſent King's Marriage was, as it were the Seal and Condition, notwithſtanding all thoſe Oaths and Promiſes this King took and made to his Father in Law, <hi>Philip</hi> IV. not to aſſiſt <hi>Portugal;</hi> no ſooner did he return to <hi>Paris,</hi> but he ſent Mounſieur <hi>Schomberg</hi> with ſome Regiments and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and all this to weaken <hi>Spain;</hi> which made a ballance with him of the Empire of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo that neither Peace, Truce, nor Promiſe, nor Proteſtation are able to ſway him, when his Intereſt is at ſtake; no, nor Religion it ſelf: How zealous a Catholick ſoever he would fain ſeem to be, is not a Fence ſtrong enough to reſtrain him, as we ſhall make appear in the following Diſcourſe</p>
               <p>When <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. ſent an Embaſſadour to the King of <hi>Siam,</hi> under the pretence of converting him, do you really believe this King endeavoured to extend his Miſſion ſo far? No no, he works no Converſion, but where he may ſend his Dragoons, who are his booted Apoſtles: It is to ſpie the Country by his Jeſuits, to endeavour by means of the Sieur <hi>Conſtance,</hi> a <hi>Venetian</hi> by Nation, and Chief Manager of that King's Affairs, to drive out other Nations, to ſettle ſome ſort of Commerce in that ſame Countrey; that he may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152962:8"/>there have certain Emiſſaries, who may ever and anon put Jealouſies into the King of <hi>Siam</hi>'s Head, by reaſon of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> growing Greatneſs in the <hi>Indies,</hi> to make the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of <hi>Bantam</hi> ſerve as a pretence, making another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of it. Obſerve the Policy of <hi>France:</hi> She hath her politick tricks which ſucceed wondrous well: This is the reaſon why ſhe ſends none but notable Men into all the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> and ſuch who are wonderful quick ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and verſed in Affairs; whom it's all one to her whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe fetch from the Camp, the Bar, or from the Church it ſelf, as occaſion ſerves; according to the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wherein ſhe would have them imployed: But more eſpecially, it is requiſite they ſhould be dextrous and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, brazen-faced, that they have the knack of promiſing fair; that they don't inſiſt too much upon certain petty ſcruples, which honeſt men ought to have: In a word, to expreſs it more intelligibly, they muſt be Cheats and Knaves; as for <hi>Spain,</hi> they moſt an end ſend thither one of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, by reaſon that every one knows, that perſons of their Character have great credit there, and in conſiderable eſteem.</p>
               <p>In <hi>England</hi> at ſuch time as the Parliament were more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werful than they be at preſent: Thither they ſent the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs <hi>De Rou'vigni,</hi> who was of the Reformed Religion, and their Delegate General at Court, and was of the very ſame temper that all the other Miniſters are, and ſwaid by the ſame politick deſigns.</p>
               <p>Into <hi>Holland</hi> they uſually ſend ſome well-ſpoken Man, who one would think would ruine his Maſter, by promiſing, from which the King never gets off, but by ſtanding to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; who does what in him lies to inſinuate himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the favour of your <hi>Dutch</hi> Ladies, either by play, or a libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral entertainment, and as they have a mighty influence upon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152962:8"/>their Husbands temper and mind, they caſt about to learn of them what they were not able to know from the Husband himſelf: Now ſeeing they began to give no credit to him who reſides there at preſent; the King, as himſelf confeſſeth in his deſtiny of Princes, was foret to ſend him his Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>France</hi> in all haſte; ſo that by this means he might be lookt upon as ſincere and infallible in whatſoever he ſhould ſay.</p>
               <p>To the Courts of <hi>Germany</hi> they diſpatch your Brawny Fellows, who are able to bare Wine well; thereby, that they may be made fit Table Companions for the Prince, whither their Commiſſion ſends them; for at the time when the third Courſe comes up, when the Wine begins to ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, they ſpeak divers things which they would not have divulged at another time: As ſaith the Proverb, <hi>In vino veritas.</hi> Don't believe that <hi>France</hi> ſends a Church-man to <hi>Rome,</hi> and why? Becauſe they are all inferiour to the Pope, and there is not the pittifulleſt Prieſt, but is confident, he ſhall be one day Cardinal; as Soldiers are, that they ſhall one day be Captains. Thither is ſent a <hi>Nogaret,</hi> who bauls aloud; and to the Popes Infallibility, oppoſes the Power and Strength of his Maſter, the King.</p>
               <p>Into other Courts, where greedineſs of Money prevails over their own Intereſt, there is not wanting preſents, and ſuch a Prince there is, who is betrayed even to his Pillow.</p>
               <p>In fine, All Weapons are convenient to this Policy of <hi>France,</hi> provided they can but bring about their Deſign: You ſee in all Courts <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Officers, and all for ſooth, for having fought Duels; but retiring out of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is not their chief buſineſs, that indeed is their pretence; but they have other aims and good inſtructions, and you ſee them after ſome time expir'd, return into <hi>France,</hi> to receive the reward of their employ; who bring along with them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152962:9"/>information concerning the ſtrength or weakneſs of the places from whence they come, which in due ſeaſon may be advantagious and uſeful to <hi>France;</hi> yet what is moſt deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, is the blindneſs of ſeveral Princes to intruſt ſuch like Men with Imployment, even among Proteſtants. Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Vauban</hi> the preſent chief Enginier of <hi>France</hi> followed this Trade particularly in <hi>Holland;</hi> 'tis confeſt, we muſt ſay, he ſerves his Maſter; but it behoves other Princes to have a ſpecial care of him. You are in the right, you ſay true, and it were to be wiſht all other Potentates would do the ſame for the quiet of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Maxime of the Policy of <hi>France</hi> is, that when any Prince or Princeſs is to be Married, that may be for their turn, he cauſes Marriages to be propoſed, and doth his utmoſt to place <hi>French</hi> Princeſſes in the Houſes of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Princes, whom they never fail to teach their Leſſon, and tell them it is their Duty, when time ſerves; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their departure, to make them acknowledge how much they are obliged to the King; and the means whereby they may render him their acknowledgments: But yet it is of freſh date, how the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> eſcaped him; not but that the <hi>French</hi> King by his Miniſters and Emiſſaries did what lay in hir power; and to his comfort, he neglected no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>Spain</hi> has been too hard for him at this time: At preſent the Policy of <hi>France</hi> is ſet a work to match the Royal Prince of <hi>Poland</hi> no queſtion with ſome Natural Daughter of the Kings, ſince they have had the boldneſs to dare to preſent ſuch an one to the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who values himſelf as much, not to mention his Right to value him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more than the Prince of <hi>Poland:</hi> Nay, I believe it had been a thing already done, had they but been ſure he would have ſucceeded to the Crown; for failing in that, he would have brought no great Advantage to <hi>France.</hi> 'Tis very
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152962:9"/>improbable the King of <hi>Poland</hi> would have refuſed her with a conſiderable Dowry; for he is already much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to the King of <hi>France,</hi> Two Hundred Thouſand Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers a year beſtowed on one of his Sons, by giving him the Abbies of St. <hi>Germain,</hi> and St. <hi>Dennis,</hi> deſerved well to be hearkned to: Beſides, the Queen ought to be well ſatisfied therewith; her Father is made Duke and Peer of France, and they have promiſed to receive her as Queen, in caſe ſhe comes into <hi>France,</hi> although ſhe be born Subject to the King of <hi>France:</hi> So that it is not at all to be queſtion'd, but that if the Crown were ſecured to the young Prince, the buſineſs would have been done e're now: There are Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes enough in <hi>France</hi> to be choſen ready for this Match. Is it not to exalt himſelf, like the Chief Monarch of <hi>Europe</hi> to erect at <hi>Metz</hi> a Souveraign Court, before which the King makes all Kings and Princes be cited, who poſſeſs any Lands, whom he ſtiles his Dependants for the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories that no wayes belong to him; they upon default of appearing, not owning this Falſe, Tyrannical, Univerſal Tribunal, he gets the Lands adjudged to him, takes poſſeſſion of them without any form of Proceſs, but by his Cannon Law. If any one contradict this, the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Monthelliard, Pettite Pierre</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and a great many other Princes will tell you, what a Monſter this Chamber is, that it devours whatſoever comes in its way; and what is yet more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable, is, that he dares ground his Right at this day to ſome Lands in <hi>Germany,</hi> upon the final determination this Chamber of <hi>Metz</hi> made in his behalf, as we ſhall ſhortly ſee in a Memorial he hath lately ſent to the Diet at <hi>Ratis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone. France</hi> hath beſides a notable Advantage to frame her Pretenſions and Titles: I mean, there are ſo many cunning Fellows in <hi>Paris,</hi> knowing ſo exactly to imitate the Ancient
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152962:10"/>
                  <hi>Gothick</hi> Character of Five or Six Hundred Years date, that one would ſwear they were in reality Authentick: Now by this means they hammer out a Dependance far fetcht, which the Devil himſelf, as cunning as he is, could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict: And then who knows what is ſtill behind the Curtain, and not come to light; which will not appear but in due time and place; when a favourable opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall require it. Can a Man forbear laughing when he hears the praiſes which theſe flatterers beſtow on <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. perſwading him he hath procured peace both to his Enemies and to all <hi>Europe.</hi> Theſe Tales are very fit to be told to the Kingdom of <hi>Siam,</hi> as Mounſieur <hi>de Chaumont,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador was not backward to do in his Speech to that King, which is to be found at large in a Book Entituled, <hi>A Voyage into Siam;</hi> and they have not been wanting in like manner to put off ſuch ſort of Trifles to the King of <hi>China;</hi> ſuch like ſtories, are good for nothing elſe but to be obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on thoſe Countreys, though not here in <hi>Europe,</hi> where our Eyes have ſeen, and Ears heard the contrary: Is it not ſtrange to meet with ſuch Writers who commit ſuch imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Trifles as theſe to paper? Don't we know what the proceedings of the King of <hi>France</hi> have been to procure a Peace with the States of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces?</hi> For ſeeing Fortune began to change, he Agreed as touching the City of <hi>Nemeghen,</hi> which belonged to the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> ſo that no body went to <hi>Verſailles,</hi> to demand it of him: He offers them <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> which was ſtill in his hands: Yea, If the <hi>States</hi> had not been ſo very haſty to grant him what he demanded, with ſo much importunity, and for which he made ſo many fair promiſes, he would have been glad to have defrayed all the Expence of the War: Pray who can tell what it hath coſt him under hand to obtain this Peace, which he ſued for with ſo much inſtant Intreaties, ſparing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152962:10"/>nothing that he might endeavour to get the <hi>States</hi> to ſlip their Necks out of the Collar, and forſake their Allies; he went ſo far as to ſurrender divers places to <hi>Spain</hi> to ſerve for boundaries between his Kingdom, and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces.</hi> In ſaying, that if the <hi>States</hi> had not been too forward to haſten on the ſigning the Peace, <hi>France</hi> would have paid the Expences of the War. I hope I do not ſpeak without good grounds for what I ſay; ſeveral Reaſons obliged them to clap up this peace in all haſte ſeparately, becauſe they ſaw their ſtrength decreaſed dayly: It is certain that after the Battle at St. <hi>Dennis,</hi> which was not fought out, by reaſon of a Peace, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> would have marcht on into <hi>France</hi> with his Troops: Moreover the King knew full well, that being forced to agitate a General Peace, it would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be effected till he ſhould ſurrender to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> all his Lands; and that he could not poſſibly induce the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> to reſtore to the <hi>Sweed,</hi> what he had taken from him according to his obligation thereto, when the Peace in particular with him was in agitation: <hi>France</hi> had a great mind to make him reſtore to the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> his Allie, what he had loſt in taking up Arms for the ſervice of <hi>France;</hi> ſo that here are your ſufficient reaſons for demanding particular Peace with the <hi>States;</hi> and that it was not he that procured it for <hi>Europe,</hi> as he boaſts and publiſheth up and down: If any one was the cauſe of Peace to the Empire, 'twas the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces;</hi> for when they had made peace at the inſtant ſupplication of the King, the General Peace followed immediately, uſher'd in by the mediation of the <hi>States General:</hi> 'Tis moſt certain, the King made this Peace by compulſion; he began to do things, but by halves; the <hi>States</hi> and his Allies reinforced themſelves dayly. The <hi>Hollanders</hi> were recovered out of their Lethargie; the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> day by day became
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152962:11"/>more experienced; the Duke of <hi>Luxemburg</hi>'s familiar Spirit grew feeble, and began to forſake him; part of the <hi>French</hi> Troops periſhed, the remainder were much haraſſed and worn out, <hi>Swedeland</hi> had done her worſt, and was at her laſt ſhifts; ſo that it was abſolutely neceſſary to afford ſome reſpite and relief to the <hi>French</hi> Troops by a Peace, being that this Peace was partly but a forc't one, the King was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to give up whatſoever he had taken; ſo alſo it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued but a ſhort while, and juſt then, when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour had his hands full of the <hi>Turk;</hi> and when the <hi>Spaniard</hi> and his Allies had laid down their Arms, and did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce upon the ſtrict performance of the Treaty of <hi>Nemeghen,</hi> the moſt Chriſtian King like a Lyon, falls foul upon the <hi>Low Countreys.</hi> Now it was convenient to ſtop this Torrent, to deliver up a good many places, and to give ground, and to patch up a Truce in the midſt of Peace, which will continue no longer than his Intereſt will permit; a body may ſay, and that truly, that <hi>France</hi> makes but ſmall difference between her Subjects and her Neighbours. <hi>Genoua</hi> may bear me witneſs of the truth of this; he treads them under foot, and fleeces them all alike, when occaſion ſerves; and when his Will and Pleaſure is, who is he that dares aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us, that the Truce will be a ſtronger Bank to put a ſtop to his Ambition, and his own private Ends, than the two Treaties of Peace of the <hi>Pyrenneans</hi> and <hi>Nemegen:</hi> That Numerous Army, that amounts to near One Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Men, which he maintains as well in Peace, and in time of Ceſſation of Arms, as in time of War; ſufficiently declares the <hi>French</hi> Policy that hath always one foot up ready, a going to march; and ſits on thorns, having ever more Armies in a readineſs to execute her deſigns: They make them Camp, and de-Camp, continually to be in motion, that they may uſe and accuſtom their Neighbours to it, for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152962:11"/>fear they ſhould give them occaſion of ſuſpition, when they march in good earneſt to fall upon any place, or ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize it.</p>
               <p>One of the King of <hi>France</hi> his Maxims, is to hinder theſe Neighbours, leſt they ſhould augment their Forces, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main alwayes in a condition, not to be able to do them harm on the ſudden, except they have a mind to have them about their Ears; as we have obſerved at ſuch time as the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> were partly reſolved to levy Sixteen Thouſand Men; what Solicitations, what deluſory Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, nay, how many Journeys did the Comte <hi>D' Avaux</hi> take to hinder it: He did nothing but talk up and down of the ſincerity and reality of the Covenants on his part, juſt as if no body beſide his Maſter had any Honeſty; and as if he were the only Man for keeping his word in Treaties: All that was, becauſe he ſaw plainly that this new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion given out, would obſtruct the taking the City of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> promiſing that there his Maſter would ſtop, and put an end to all his Claims and Demands: But he is ſtill as ready to take another, as he was before the taking of this City, as we ſaw lately at <hi>Mons;</hi> it would be all one whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>States</hi> ſhould oppoſe this proceeding, or no; it would be ſo long as the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> ſhould ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be hood-winkt by baſe fear, or complaiſance, wonderful advantagious indeed to promote the deſigns of <hi>France</hi> in <hi>Europe;</hi> no body taking notice that <hi>France</hi> is as ſordid as her Maſter; and that both of them are afraid of cold Iron.</p>
               <p>All theſe new Converſions of ſome, and Perſecutions of others which we ſee in <hi>France,</hi> is nothing but to blind the Catholick Princes, and to amuſe them ſo long, till he fall upon ſome City or State, profeſſing the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: The Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> knows too well this Stratagem;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152962:12"/>ſhe practiſed it her ſelf heretofore, when ſhe had higher deſigns on foot than now ſhe hath; when ſhe attacked a Proteſtant Prince, her pretence then was that ſhe would Extirpate Hereſie: This is the <hi>French</hi> King's trade at this day; it was expedient for him out of meer neceſſity to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at home with his own Subjects; and as that could not chooſe but have weaken'd him, he ſolicites others to do as much as he: What pains hath he taken to ſet the <hi>Swiſſe</hi> at variance, and induce the Catholick <hi>Cantons</hi> to fall out with the Proteſtants, and then afterwards, when they are at odds, to fall upon them? But the Pope hath redreſſed that, and accommodated the matter betwixt them. <hi>France</hi> hath brought it ſo to paſs, that ſhe hath forced the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to rid himſelf of his beſt Subjects, the Inhabitants of the Vallies being under a premunier as he is, he could not go back with his word; nay, I am fully perſwaded, <hi>France</hi> would be extreamly glad that <hi>England</hi> would do the like; by that means to weaken her to ſuch a degree, that ſhe ſhall not be able to do any thing, when <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. has a mind to fall upon the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> and remove from the <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> all poſſible means to prevent it; and ſo by little and little, make himſelf Maſter of <hi>Europe;</hi> as we ſhall ſee by the following ſtory of the <hi>French</hi> Policy, and its Maxims, in reſpect of Soveraigns in particular.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Policy of <hi>France,</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Rome,</hi> and His <hi>Holineſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL the World knows the Veneration and Reſpect all Catholick People have for the Holy See, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father that they look upon him as Chriſt's Vicar upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152962:12"/>Earth, St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſſor, Univerſal Biſhop, and as we are taught by the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> the moſt Holy Lord, to whom all Kings, Princes, and People owe an intire Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; fail but in this Duty, and you ſmell rank of Hereſie; according to the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> it deſerves Fire and Faggot. Would you not ſwear to ſee <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Proteſtants at that rate he doth; that he is the moſt Devout Son his Holineſs hath, whereas others do but kiſs his Toe; he would out of Devotion kiſs ſomething elſe: But it is quite contrary: He is a very Rebellious Son, who cares not a fig for all the Holy Father's Remonſtrances and Declarations, who diſpoyles him of his Goods, raviſhes from him his State, and makes an entry into <hi>Rome</hi> by his Embaſſador, as loftily and haughtily as <hi>Artaban.</hi> And here is the <hi>French</hi> Spirit to invade the Holy Father in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, Authority, and Conduct: Firſt, In his Patrimony of the Church, by depriving him of his Regalities in <hi>France;</hi> which is a Right the Popes have enjoyed this many Ages; which the Kings, <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. his Predeceſſors have granted to St. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſors: What Submiſſion, what Remonſtrance hath not the preſent Pope made to oblige the King not to incroach and ſeize upon the Rights of the Church; withal telling him, that ſuch like Uſurpations as theſe, have proved alwayes ſatal to Kings and Princes Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies? Yet all this hath had none effect upon him; only the King ſaid ſometimes, <hi>the Pope is a mighty good man, I would not vex him:</hi> But in the mean time, never reſtores what he had deprived him of. Juſt ſuch another trick as he played with <hi>Spain,</hi> when in time of Peace he took from it part of the <hi>Low Countreys;</hi> he proteſted every where that he had no Intent to break the Peace, but only took his Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dances, and what of Right was his own. You may turn the <hi>French</hi> Policy looſe which way you will; it preſently finds
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152962:13"/>out a way to oblige his Holineſs to permit an Aſſembly of the Clergy of his Kingdom in the year 1682, wherein it was declared, as we all know, that he was not Infallible; that he had no Power over the Temporalities of Kings, that he was ſubject to Counſels, and by himſelf he had not any power to make any one Article of Faith. Could he have thwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Pope more ſenſibly in his Authority than he did at that time; beſides, he obliged all the Preachers, Monks and Jeſuits themſelves, to teach the ſame in the Pulpit, and in their Colledges to their Auditors. The Arch-biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> who was Preſident of this Aſſembly, who as you may well think, was not too well beloved at <hi>Rome?</hi> thought at leaſt it was fit to make himſelf fear'd, that they might come and offer him a Cardinals Cap. To this effect he writ into <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> to be informed what courſe <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. took when he altered the Religion in that Kingdom; yet all this had not the leaſt effect upon the Popes mind, who knows his own Tribe better than ſo; and Mounſieur Arch-biſhop was in great danger to ſtand bare a long time without a Cardinals Cap, although he might catch cold: When this Prelate perceived that by this means his Affairs went rather back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard than forward, he bethought himſelf of another courſe, prefers himſelf, and takes upon him, not like a Converter, but Perſecutor; in cauſing the Hugonots of his Dioceſs to be tormented, and thoſe of all <hi>France</hi> by his wicked Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, hoping thereby to curry favour with the Pope, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain his credit by his zeal and forwardneſs for the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion. But his Holineſs, who hath abundance of reaſon, and whoſe diſpoſition is not violent, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and meaning is, that Converſions ſhould be effected by Reaſon, by good Examples; not by Dragoons and Rackings, and by an Holy Life, which is not conſiſtant with the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> who is taken with the Female Sex, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152962:13"/>love their Company: This change of ſhapes procured him but ill will and diſdain; he had no ſhare in the laſt promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor never will ſo long as <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. lives, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps after him; when of neceſſity there will happen great changes at <hi>Rome:</hi> In the mean time Mounſieur <hi>Camus,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Grenoble</hi> (whoſe unblameable Life and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might ſerve for a Mirrour to a many of your Court Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops) hath been honoured with the Purple without ever ſeeking for it, without perſecuting any body, nor ſo much as ſuffering it within his Dioceſs; this Prelate being not <hi>a-la-mode de la Court,</hi> this new Dignity he ſo lately recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, cannot chooſe but be a great heart-burning to the King, and greater to the Arch-biſhop, to ſee himſelf ſhut out of doors? Laſt of all, Can a Man more viſibly croſs the Popes behaviour, than the King doth at preſent in reſpect of the Franchiſes of his Embaſſador's Quarters, which ſerved only for a Sanctuary for Robbers, Bankrupts, and ſeveral Aſſaſſinates; nay, more to fill the Embaſſador's, or his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Servants Purſes? Although the Pope be Maſter in his own Houſe, yet he hath had the prudence to expect the death of the Count <hi>Deſtrees,</hi> Embaſſadour; and the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Embaſſador of <hi>Spain;</hi> yet what a clutter make they at the <hi>French</hi> Court about the regulation the Pope makes for ſecurity of his Subjects, and the quiet of his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital City? I would fain know if the Pope intermeddles with what the King doth at <hi>Paris,</hi> or whether he did think it convenient, to ſpeak againſt the Effigies of the King; which they have placed now in his Life-time, in the middle of Four Lanterns, in the place <hi>de Victor,</hi> with leud Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to which the Magiſtracy and Regiments of Guards did Obeyſance, and Honoured as the King himſelf, even ſo far as to make Speeches to it. I would have any body ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie me how the King would have taken their bare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152962:14"/>of the Pope; without doubt he would have anſwered him, that he might meddle with his own buſineſs, and that every one is Maſter of his own. When his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs not approving the King's too familiar acquaintance with Madam <hi>de Monteſpan,</hi> and correſpondence with Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> when he ſignified to the General of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, that he was much ſurprized, that Father <hi>La Chaize</hi> made no more of giving him abſolution, the King appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be very much diſſatisfied therewith; and ſaid, he was bound to give an account to no body of his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Why did he cauſe his Embaſſador to make his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance as it were, with Sword in hand: All this doth make the temper of <hi>France</hi> to appear, which would domineer eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where over all, even over the Altar it ſelf.</p>
               <p>But let the King make what noiſe he will, as theſe Franchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes bring him no profit, ſo there would be ſome way found out to pacifie all things, if his Holineſs would grant a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation for a Marriage of the Eldeſt Son of the Church to a Daughter of <hi>Rome,</hi> (I mean the City of <hi>Liege</hi>) I would ſay, by means of a Bull for the Cardinal of <hi>Furſtenburg,</hi> in caſe he could get himſelf elected Coadjutor to the Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Cologne,</hi> not being in a capacity to be Arch-biſhop of <hi>Cologne</hi> himſelf; to avoid falling under the ſame Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that the aforeſaid Arch-biſhop did upon the account of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Munſter,</hi> for which he never could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Bull, how inſtant ſoever the ſolicitations have been by the late Embaſſador of <hi>France</hi> for obtaining the ſame; but it is enough for the <hi>French</hi> King, ſince no body at preſent can be admitted to it; who is averſe to his Intereſts. Now if <hi>Fuſtenburg</hi> that <hi>Mercury</hi> of <hi>France</hi> ſhould chance to be ſo dignified, it is odds, but that the zeal for his Maſter and Benefactor would be augmented, and that nothing but this Temper and Policy of <hi>France</hi> would Reign, by reaſon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152962:14"/>of him throughout the Electoral Dominions; nay, an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to one, but the King who would have a Garriſon in the Fortreſs, would become Abſolute Maſter. But 'tis to be hoped, that for the benefit of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the Church, that his Holineſs will never make ſuch a falſe ſtep, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his own Intereſts, and to all Chriſtian People, as to grant theſe Bulls to Cardinal <hi>Furſtenburg:</hi> We all know very well, if once the King could be without the Pope, he could ſave himſelf the trouble of going to <hi>Rome,</hi> and could conſtitute and eſtabliſh a Patriarch in <hi>France,</hi> after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the <hi>Greeks;</hi> no queſtion he would do it, conſidering what was reſolved on theſe few years laſt paſt by the <hi>French</hi> Clergy: There would be a two-fold advantage by it; the Mony that is carried to <hi>Rome,</hi> would not go out of <hi>France;</hi> the Patriarch would grant him whatſoever he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire (as Parliaments do at preſent) were it even a Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation to marry the Princeſs of <hi>Conty.</hi> But he cannot ſhake off the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> beſides, the Jeſuits would be upon his back, if he ſhould not appoint Father <hi>La Chaize,</hi> or ſome one of their Society, Patriarch. On the other hand, thoſe Biſhops that aſpire to be Cardinals, would not be well pleaſed with this new invention, except the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> who could have ſome pretence to this Dignity; who in plain terms doth already ſay, That the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> ſince <hi>Henry</hi> VIII, till <hi>Charles</hi> II. have done well enough without <hi>Rome;</hi> beſides, what the Northern Kings do at this time. That which makes the <hi>French</hi> King temporize ſo much, is, by reaſon he knows Popes are not as the King is ſaid to be in the Inſcription, <hi>viro immortali;</hi> that next after this Pope there may come another, who perhaps may not prove ſo honeſt a Man, yet may comply more with the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son of the Church; but new Lords, new Laws: Death may as well cruſh, and bring down diſeaſed Kings, as crazy
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152962:15"/>Popes. Be ſure you may expect to ſee this politick Humour of <hi>France</hi> within a little while cock up in <hi>Avignon,</hi> and the Country of <hi>Veneſſin,</hi> as much as we ſee it at this day in <hi>Metz, Sedam, Franch Conte, Burgundy, Dombes,</hi> and laſt of all in the Principality of <hi>Orange.</hi> The King hath the ſame right of re-Union, convenience of Scituation over <hi>Avignon,</hi> and the County <hi>Veneſſin,</hi> as he hath over all the other Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, I have but juſt named; for Q. <hi>Jane</hi> could not alienate the Crown-Lands to Pope <hi>Clement</hi> V. ſo that the Popes to disburſe Thirty Thouſand Florens to keep it, ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. The Country of <hi>Veneſſin</hi> was taken from the Count <hi>de St. Gille,</hi> ſo that albeit the Holy Sea had had the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe two places for ſome years; yet be ſure the King will one of theſe days find an opportunity, whether by breeding a Quarrel, or otherwiſe to get it into his Clutches: That once done, the Pope may cry out long enough, he will be in a fair way, if he hold not his Tongue to make his Son ſend ſome Troops againſt St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as hath been done not long ago; and if ever the <hi>French</hi> King make himſelf Maſter of <hi>Spain,</hi> as he pretends by right ſo to be, after the deceaſe of <hi>Charles</hi> now Reigning; the Pope muſt not think that his Rights will be better preſerved at that time in <hi>Spain,</hi> than they be now in <hi>France,</hi> and the Dignity of <hi>Exarchat</hi> of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venna,</hi> which <hi>Pepin</hi> granted to the Holy See, would ſoon change its Maſter, and who can tell whether <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf would be exempted, ſo ſoon as ever the Pope ſhould begin to ſpeak of Excommunication, the King would ſpeak of a Patriarch, inſomuch that the Pope ought not to flatter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that the politick diſpoſition of <hi>France</hi> will truckle to the Holy See, nor to make an eſtimate of the King, how much a Catholick he is by the Perſecution he raiſes againſt the Hugonots within his own Realms and Dominions, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; he knows well enough what he doth: If he perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152962:15"/>them with one hand, he helps them with the other, he knows how to bring the <hi>Turk</hi> into <hi>Hungary,</hi> when he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth them fit for his Deſigns and Intereſts againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; when he thinks they may be ſerviceable to him as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants in advancing him to the Throne of <hi>Europe,</hi> to which our Great King hath confined his Ambition: But it often happens that Man purpoſes, but God diſpoſes. <hi>France</hi> would have you believe her true-hearted and real, that the Holy See, and every body beſides ſhould of her Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on make an Article of their Creed: Let her do and ſay what ſhe pleaſes; I do not for all that believe, that if ſo be Faith and Truth were loſt, that any one would go look to find it in <hi>France:</hi> All her by-paſt Actions do but too much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak her, not to be any longer honeſt, and that Faith cannot agree with the King's Humour; ſo that a Prince fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that, the Holy Father ought to beware of him; he is a cloſe Enemy, counterfeiting the <hi>Devoto;</hi> a whited Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre that dazles the Eyes of thoſe who approach him: He is an <hi>Orpheus,</hi> who charms Chriſtendom by his kind promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and noiſe of his <hi>Louiſes dor,</hi> but within he is a very ſink of Falſhood, inſatiable Ambition, of unparallel'd Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of barbarous Cruelty; from whoſe Cruelty, and out of whoſe Hands the Church ſhould put it into their Litany, Good Lord, deliver us, for fear they Chriſtians fall into the ſame miſeries that the <hi>Jews</hi> did in the time of <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Illuſtrious.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Policy of <hi>France,</hi> in relation to the Emperour and Princes Electors of the Empire.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHarles</hi> V. did manifeſtly weaken the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> by dividing it into two branches; beſtowing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152962:16"/>the Empire on <hi>Ferdinand</hi> his Brother, and <hi>Spain</hi> to <hi>Philip</hi> his Son: I muſt needs confeſs that theſe are two Twins, ſo nearly related to each other by Blood, by Alliances, and common Intereſts, that one will have much ado to touch the one, without offending the other; or deſtroy the one, without debilitating and reducing the other to the utmoſt extremity: This Houſe hath evermore held up her Head againſt <hi>France;</hi> ſhe alwayes counterpoized with <hi>France</hi> the Empire of the World: <hi>Spain</hi> took from <hi>Antony</hi> of <hi>Bourbon</hi> King of <hi>Navar,</hi> the Kingdom he had acquired by his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with <hi>Jane De Albret,</hi> Heireſs of <hi>Navar;</hi> ſo that 'tis eaſie to ſuppoſe, that at preſent the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon</hi> being exalted to the Throne of <hi>France</hi> ſince <hi>Henry</hi> IV. time, may be from its Cradle Enemy to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> and if ſhe could de-Throne both of them, no queſtion ſhe would with all her heart get into their place if ſhe could, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by joyn the Empire to <hi>France, France</hi> to <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countreys;</hi> and then by and by very eaſily aſcend to the Univerſal Monarchy of all <hi>Europe:</hi> If this project don't ſucceed, 'tis at leaſtwiſe the intent and purpoſe of the <hi>French</hi> Politick Spirit, and what <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. drives at; who was not far from effecting it, when <hi>Vienna</hi> look't upon her ſelf near deſtruction, and an hundred to one but had fallen into the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Chains: Scarce any one is ignorant of the Correſpondence the King of <hi>France</hi> holds with the <hi>Ottoman Port,</hi> that it was upon his intreaty that the Grand Seigniour firſt violated the Truce concluded with the Emperour, that he might ſecond and abet Count <hi>Tekely</hi>'s Deſigns, whom <hi>France</hi> aſſiſted with Money and Counſel. The Emperour and his Council knows better than any body the occaſion that moved the <hi>Port</hi> to ſend back Count <hi>Caprara,</hi> together with the Propoſitions of Peace he brought along with him. The Marquiſs <hi>D'Seppeville,</hi> Embaſſador of <hi>France,</hi> failed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152962:16"/>not with all expedition to ſend one Courier after another to his Maſter to give him notice thereof; who failed not forthwith to diſpatch a Perſon to the Grand Viſier, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him to perſiſt in his Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> he laying before him that his Honour was ingaged, that the City was at the laſt gaſp, that it ſtood him upon to take it at what rate ſoever for his own Reputations ſake, and good of the <hi>Port;</hi> that this Siege having made ſuch a noiſe in the World, he could not quit it, but with Eternal Infamy to the <hi>Ottaman</hi> Empire and Grand Viſier, and for the better facilitating the taking of it, and to divide the Armies of the Empire, he was about to enter into <hi>Flanders</hi> with a powerful Army, which would undoubtedly force the Empire to recal his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to defend themſelves; and the King did effectually make good his promiſe; for he entered of late years as we ſee into <hi>Flanders,</hi> burning, pillaging, and taking all before him after the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> manner, imitating therein his Allie, whom he was ſo forward to ſerve and ſecond; and the King di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſting himſelf of the Title of Moſt Chriſtian, took upon him that of his Friend, and Allie the Grand Sultan; for pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that ought to be moſt ſacred to Chriſtians, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirements of the Nuns fared no better: Several Virgins ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Martyrdom by a Violation never before heard of in Chriſtendom: But all this did much contribute to the King's Deſign, and the <hi>French</hi> Policy obtained its wiſh; there was Forty Thouſand Men juſt ready in <hi>Alſatia</hi> to pour into <hi>Germany,</hi> to make himſelf be declared Emperour at the Head of this Army: His Manifeſtoes were already in print, ready to be ſpread abroad; that to prevent Chriſtianity from falling into Slavery, he was forced to withſtand it by a powerful Army, and by declaring himſelf Emperour to hold the Reins of the Empire, to defend it, as ſerving as a boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary to <hi>France,</hi> and to <hi>Europe</hi> it ſelf; conſidering the inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152962:17"/>of the Emperour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the King knew what he ſaid when he tells us the Emperour was not fit to Reign: Without all queſtion, had <hi>Vienna</hi> been taken, the Princes and Electors would have had recourſe to him, and been of his ſide, for their own preſervation; being the only Prince who had Forces ready, and who at that juncture was capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to retard the progreſs of the Infidels. But <hi>Vienna</hi> being relieved, we ſaw then the truth of what I have alledged, that their Spirit came down, and they became creſt-fallen, they cared not to joyn in the common joy of all the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, which could not ſufficiently praiſe God for this Signal Victory, by their Bone-fires, and <hi>Te Deums,</hi> wherewith the Air echoed again: None but <hi>France</hi> ſtood mute, and who forbid divers Church-men to give thanks for the ſame, upon pain of incurring the high diſpleaſure of the moſt Chriſtian King. Here you may perceive what Spirit <hi>France</hi> is of, in relation to the Emperour; who, that it might have an opportunity to keep him under, and throw him down from his Throne, and ſo take his place; The King of <hi>France</hi> heartily wiſhes that <hi>Vienna</hi> might ſall into the hands of the <hi>Mahometans:</hi> But as our Thoughts are not as Gods Thoughts, ſo this King of Kings has diſpoſed of things otherwiſe; who by vouchſafing ſuch grand Victories to the Chriſtian Forces, <hi>France</hi> muſt be fain to change their Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries and Aſſaults. We hope alſo that the Emperours Council will ſtand better upon their Guard, and appear more vigilant than they have been hitherto; and that they will remove from <hi>France</hi> all means to pry into their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings; yea, even into their Cloſet-ſecrets: For 'tis well known what courſes they have taken to make the Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be changed and falſified, when they were not reliſhed by the King, nor for his Intereſt; and that the Emperour could neither ſpeak, conſult, write, nor ſo much as make
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152962:17"/>leaſt proceeding, but it was preſently penetrated, diverted another way, incumbred, watched and obſerved; and by the Jeſuits good leave they are accuſed of having had a great ſtroak in all theſe Affairs; they always take the ſtronger ſide, expecting a change. No body can be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant but that the miſ-underſtanding that aroſe between the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and <hi>Monticuculi,</hi> General of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Forces, during the <hi>Holland</hi> War; was occaſion'd by the cunning contrivance of the Jeſuite changing the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Order, to ingage <hi>Turrene</hi> with <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> in the counterfeit Order not to engage; which gave opportunity to the <hi>French</hi> Army to retreat; which was in very great danger to have made their Graves there, if it had been at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacked by two ſo good Parties, being reduced to its laſt legs through ſickneſſes, running away from their Colours, and a Mortality amongſt them.</p>
               <p>Then again, At the Battel at <hi>Sennif, Souches</hi> excuſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he could not make the on-ſet for want of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; this was hammered upon the ſame Anvil: Yet we hope that Affairs changing their Face, the Reverend Fathers the Jeſuits will have better thoughts of the Empire. I have much ado to omit two Affairs which happened during the Emperors laſt Rupture with the King; one is the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of General <hi>Capelliers</hi> Steward of his Houſhold; who carryed on a correſpondence with the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadors, and gave them a full account of whatſoever paſt at home in his Maſters Houſe, that came to his hearing, or knowledge; the Letters of all the Matter were intercepted at the Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe in <hi>Frankfort;</hi> this Traytor indeed was clapt up, but the Jeſuits who at that bout had taken too large a Doſe of Spirit Gall, knew well enongh how to make him come of, leſt he ſhould make a Diſcovery of ſome others. During the Siege of <hi>Philipsburg</hi> by the Imperial Forces, did not
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152962:18"/>theſe good Men prevail with two Merchants to ſend in a ſupply of Powder, but that Mine was ſprung, and vaniſht in ſmoak; the buſineſs was found out, and the Jeſuits brought it ſo about, that the undertakers were not puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for fear leſt they ſhould make farther Diſcoveries; I tell you this for truth; for one of theſe Perſons was one of my Acquaintance, who told it me with his own mouth, that they came to fetch him as far as from <hi>Paris,</hi> where he was ſettled, to get him to do this buſineſs: You may ſee by this, that the Spirit of <hi>France</hi> animates a great many Bodies, actuates them ſtrangely; and that thoſe in whom his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Majeſty puts moſt confidence, are not always faithful to him. When <hi>France</hi> carried on a deſign under-hand to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Emperour to beſtow his two Siſters upon two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces diſpoſſeſt of their Inheritance; it was not with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that buſineſſes ſhould ſucceed in this manner as we ſee they do at this day; for we cannot deny but that <hi>Lorrain</hi> is the Reſtorer of the Empire, an <hi>Hero</hi> of ſo many Great and Glorious Victories, the Subduer of ſo many Provinces, who will make the Grand Seigniour not only ſue to him for Peace, as he doth already, but to grant whatſoever one demands of him to ſave his Head from the riot and fury of the Rabble, who will be ſure to do it, if he conclude not a Peace, or a Ceſſation of Arms, and that ſpeedily. But this Spirit of <hi>France</hi> had its aims; that is to ſay, by getting ſome body to counſel the Emperour to beſtow his two Siſters on two Princes in the forementioned Circumſtances, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaired of recovering their Eſtates but by a Peace; they would alwayes incline the Emperour to liſten thereto, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his Imperial Majeſty might not have that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by it that might be expected; in hopes there might be ſome Article in it favourable to them, reſtoring them to their Eſtates by this Peace. The truth is, that hath been
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152962:18"/>very ſucceſsful to the one, as for the other, it is to be hoped, that he will open himſelf a paſſage to his Fortune by his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Sword: 'Tis moſt certain that the miſunderſtanding which hath reigned between Prince <hi>Harman</hi> of <hi>Baden,</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the Imperial Council, and the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Emperour, are nothing but Eggs which <hi>France</hi> ſits and hatches. The Marquiſs <hi>De Bethune</hi> is too well verſt in the way to <hi>Poland;</hi> and his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hath ſtill a <hi>French</hi> Soul, though Queen of that Kingdom. The kindneſſes the King of <hi>France</hi> has done her Children, are faithful, and living Witneſſes, and the tranſmitments that have paſt through the hands of the Bankers of <hi>Hamburg</hi> and <hi>Dantzik</hi> are like ſo many rayes of that great Sun of <hi>France,</hi> which diſperſeth his Light into a great many Courts. The Emperour cannot ignore that Itch of theirs is an old Diſtemper the Kings of <hi>France</hi> have ſo long been troubled with; they long to be mounting the Imperial Throne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is one ſtep to the Univerſal; or at leaſt, to the Monarchy of <hi>Europe. Henry</hi> II. made them draw him out the Model after what manner the <hi>Romans</hi> cut out their way through <hi>Italy;</hi> but thoſe Countreys have ever been <hi>Caemite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium Gallorum,</hi> and fatal to their Enterpriſes. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Dupleſſis</hi> gave advice to <hi>Charles</hi> IX. never to venture up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Italy,</hi> but upon the <hi>Netherlands. Lewis</hi> XIV. is much of his mind, as ſhall appear by the ſequel of the Story. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Death of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> III. did not the <hi>French</hi> King uſe his utmoſt endeavours to re-aſcend the Throne of <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main;</hi> he ſpared not to ſend into all the Courts of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors to procure their Votes; and ſuch who were great with theſe Princes, did their buſineſs for them; for <hi>France</hi> is free-natur'd enough, when any one is to be brought over to their Party: One of the viſible demonſtrations of the Kings deſigns is, that he cauſed an Eagle to be put upon his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152962:19"/>Money juſt above the Head of his Effigies; and that he ſpeaks his mind freely, but much more haughtily, that the Empire hath been long enough in the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and that it is high time it ſhould return to his again; and that was juſt upon the <hi>Turks</hi> coming into <hi>Germany,</hi> in the year 1683. But Man purpoſeth, God diſpoſeth: All the wiſe projects and contrivances of Men are but folly before God, who doth not guide the Oeconomy of the Univerſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ambition of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great: Now becauſe this King knows very well that the Electors may prove a great obſtacle to his deſign upon the Empire if they have a mind to be croſs; therefore he makes much of ſome, threatens others. The <hi>Dolphin</hi> of <hi>Frances</hi> Marriage concluded with the Princeſs of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> was a bait to draw in the Prince of that Family to the King's Intereſt, and ſo inſpire his Body with a <hi>French</hi> Spirit: That Penſion the King allowed him for ſome time made him much in the Kings Books, and devoted to his Intereſt; nay, over and above the Marriage every one was in the mind that this Prince would be perpetually devoted to his Benefactor; but the unbecoming unworthy Matches that <hi>France</hi> offered this Prince, made his Miniſters look about them; who knew ſo well how to diſabuſe him, that he alter'd his mind, and tack't about to the better and more glorious ſide, whether we conſider it in reſpect of the Marriage he contracted with the Emperours Daughter, or by the Lawrels he won in <hi>Hungary.</hi> This is a thing he durſt not ſo much as have dreamt of, if he had remained in the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt; becauſe the Conqueſts of the Imperial Army did not at all correſpond with the Kings deſigns, as we told you before: No ſooner had Mounſieur <hi>Baviere</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the <hi>French</hi> Party, but the King to comfort himſelf up for that loſs, entering <hi>Madam la Dauphines</hi> Chamber, told her that he juſt came from winning Eight Hundred Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152962:19"/>Crowns of her Brother. We all know how the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> is beſet on all ſides with the Emiſſaries of <hi>France,</hi> and how the chief perſons of his Court, which diſcretion makes me forbear mentioning, have taken but too large a Doſe of that ſame <hi>Spirit Gall;</hi> ſo that there is nothing tranſacted in the Electors Court, but the <hi>French</hi> Envoy hath preſently notice of it, and by Mounſieur <hi>de Rebenack</hi>'s good leave, Men are ſufficiently informed of all his Intrigues, of all the Preſents he beſtows; if it were leſs ſecret, one might not perchance know it; but he wanting the retentive faculty to keep his own Counſel, he muſt give others leave to diſcloſe it, who are not ſo much concern'd to keep a ſecret. If the late Prince <hi>Lewis</hi> had been ſurer to the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt than he was, perhaps he might have been alive to this day: Well, I know the <hi>French</hi> Envoy had not an hand in the fact, but did ſuggeſt and promote it: I know that the Prince Elector is not ignorant neither, whence the Diſtemper proceeds; he hath reaſon to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine them, and ſtand upon his Guard; but I could wiſh, he may not be too ſlow, and that he ſhut not the Stable door when the Horſe is ſtoln. If ſo be the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg</hi> had an inſight into his real true Intereſt and Forces; could but get rid once of theſe <hi>French</hi> Spirits that encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs her; he might ſafely ſay he was one of the moſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant Princes of the North, make others dread and ſtand in awe of him: Be ſure which way ſoever he takes, he caſts the ſcales, <hi>France</hi> knows it very well too, and that's the reaſon why they court him ſo much: Let him but ſtand Neuter, and eſpouſe no Cauſe, ſhe is ſatisfied. The Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of the Proteſtants of <hi>France</hi> had in a manner open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the eyes of the Elector; yet Mounſieur <hi>de Rebenack,</hi> backt by Mounſieur <hi>D'eſpenſe,</hi> managed things ſo finely, that people gave more credit to what they ſaid, than to ſo
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152962:20"/>many thouſand Witneſſes that arrived dayly at <hi>Berlin.</hi> This i'le ſay, that the Elector hath this benefit, that all thoſe that flie to him for refuge, people his Country: But <hi>France</hi> out of ſpite to thwart his deſigns to make the Electorſhip fall after the Deceaſe of <hi>Frederick William</hi> to ſome Prince or other, who will be more favourable to him, than thoſe who were born by the Princeſs <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> and <hi>Orange;</hi> and there is all the probability imaginable ſhe will accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh her deſigns in this matter; at leaſtwiſe they are in a fair way towards it, if God Almighty do not prevent it, by preſerving the Prince Elector alive, to whom he may give Iſſue.</p>
               <p>As for the Elector <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> when <hi>France</hi> mediated a match between the Princeſs, and the Duke of <hi>Orleans;</hi> ſhe had two things in her eye; the firſt was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by together with a Penſion to allure the late Prince Elector into her Intereſts; not being able to do that, he might evermore deviſe pretenſions for the Right of Madam of <hi>Orleans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After that we know but too well how the Electors <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> Father and Son were treated by <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. how the <hi>Palatinate</hi> hath been trodden under foot by his Troops and the people of that Country ruin'd and laid waſte: But laſt of all Death having deprived the World of theſe two Princes in a ſhort time without Male Iſſue; and ſeeing that at preſent the <hi>Palatinate</hi> is fallen to the Houſe of <hi>Newburg,</hi> (purſuant to a Treaty with the Emperour to that purpoſe) the King of <hi>France</hi> is perſwaded there is no other reſolution to take with the Elector now Reigning, that he is too near an Allie to the Emperour (to whom he is beholden for what he hath) ever to abandon his Intereſts, or quit his Party; ſo that it is not thereabouts neither, that <hi>France</hi> attacks it, the pretenſes of Madams Rights are now in debate: The
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152962:20"/>Popes medling in the matter ſignifies nothing; the buſineſs is not ripe; it is a Gate <hi>France</hi> keeps open, for to enter into <hi>Germany</hi> by; and all the delayes the Pope obtains do but keep off the Diſtemper a little longer, and do not cure it; and you ſhall ſee the next Spring (if any change happen in <hi>Europe, France</hi> will enter thereinto with Fire and Sword, as ſhe uſes to do. All the Elector muſt wiſh for is, that Peace may be concluded between the two Emperours this Winter, that the Death of a Prince hapning, his ſucceſs may afford work enough to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great ſomewhere elſe: Now theſe ſeem to be the only means how this Elector may avoid falling into the clutches of <hi>France;</hi> and this reaſon ought much to ſway with the Emperour, and be a principal mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to him to make a Peace with the <hi>Turk,</hi> as he may now do very advantagiouſly: For he muſt know, that if ever the <hi>French</hi> King break the Ice, and gets footing in <hi>Germany;</hi> he will never return back: The <hi>French</hi> are very inſolent and domineering, eſpecially at the firſt heat, and in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and provided Fortune ſmiles upon them at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and in their firſt furie; wherewith they undertake all Exploits, that is a great incitement to them to drive on farther and farther, and then peace with the <hi>Turk</hi> not being made, I cannot tell whether the Emperour will be ever able to make it, if he would never ſo fain, at leſt upon the ſame Terms and Conditions they offer him at this time.</p>
               <p>The Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> never made much account of all the propoſals of <hi>France:</hi> He is a Prince that doth not ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy all thoſe cunning niceties and tricks that a great many other Courts are full of, but one who being well verſt in what is good for himſelf, purſues it, without diſputing, or making more ado: Now that's your beſt Policy which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the beſt; wherefore <hi>France</hi> ſeeing he would not ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the hook, breeds abundance of trouble in his Family,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152962:21"/>and ſets him at variance with his Neighbours, againſt which the Emperours Council hath made ſeaſonable proviſion, which makes the Spirit of <hi>France</hi> that it becomes not ſo fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar in that Court, for their <hi>Ducatoons</hi> are better beloved than <hi>Lewiſſes:</hi> But to know what it done there, thither is ſent ſuch Perſons who have skill to comply and conform to the humour of the Country, and more eſpecially to quaff ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and by that means render themſelves fit Companions at Table; they muſt be of ſtrong Conſtitution to bear Wine; there they may get acquaintance, make themſelves familiar, and make bold to skip their Glaſſes. So likewiſe at the <hi>French</hi> Court, when an Envoy or Reſident is to be ſent to the Court of <hi>Saxony;</hi> they inquire in the firſt place whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he can hold out well at drinking, that's one Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, together with couzening, that is requiſite.</p>
               <p>As for the Electors of <hi>Triers</hi> and <hi>Metz,</hi> as <hi>France</hi> are not afraid of them, as not being Princes that are capable of doing much miſchief, ſo they let them alone till time ſerves; for ſhe knows that ſtanding in need of them, ſhe will be able to attract them by the ſweet charmes of her golden rayes; if not, ſhe will proceed to threatnings, and thereby make her do what ſhe pleaſes. The King needs no more but ſend his Forces to <hi>Triers,</hi> he hath reduc't it to ſuch a condition as not to be in a capacity to diſpute his entrance, and ſo he can make himſelf Maſter of it, when he thinks fit.</p>
               <p>As for the Elector of <hi>Cologne,</hi> we all know what mettle he is made of; that he's a Prince that loves a quiet Life, and deſiring to end his dayes in peace; gives himſelf wholly up to his Devotions, to work out his Salvation; this deſign being alwayes commendable in a Prelate, and a Perſon of his Character. But a mild peaceable diſpoſition doth no wayes agree with that of <hi>France,</hi> which is turbulent, boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152962:21"/>and would alwayes be in action: Now here is the reaſon why they have given the Arch-biſhop a chip of the old block, who hath a good ſtock of the <hi>French</hi> Spirit: I mean the Cardinal Biſhop of <hi>Strasbourg,</hi> who is as vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and as great a cheat, as he that animates him; nevertheleſs this Biſhop hath got the art ſo well, to influence the mind of the Arch-biſhop, that he rules him with an abſolute ſway, and by means of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Munſter,</hi> which <hi>France</hi> procured him with Two Millions of Crowns, cannot handſomly turn tail at preſent. I know the Pope upon very juſt conſiderations hath not been wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to diſpatch the Bull hitherto; yet it is enough for <hi>France,</hi> that by this Election, during the Electors Life; the Chapter dare never let it enter into their thoughts, much leſs ſupply the place; ſo that <hi>France</hi> is ſure that no one Prelate of a contrary party, ſhall ever be admitted to that dignity, and that ſufficeth. How many Biſhops are there in <hi>France</hi> without Bulls, who notwithſtanding perform the Functions of their place, and enjoy the benefits of their Biſhopricks. The Pope cannot live for ever, and the King will be ſure to keep the Gate open, and High-wayes clear; that after the Arch-biſhops deceaſe, ſome other Emiſſary of <hi>France</hi> may come in at the ſame Golden Gate: This Biſhoprick being of great conſequence as himſelf did acknowledge it to be in the year 1672. I told you that the Biſhop of <hi>Cologne</hi> would have much ado to free himſelf from the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt, the King having taken care for that beforehand, in caſe of a change; and all that was done at <hi>Liege,</hi> was but a cunning ſtratagem, and that through the ſuggeſtion of that Prince, to foment miſ-underſtanding between them, and to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Citizens of <hi>Liege</hi> the Idea of their diſcontent, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Cittadel which they have again raiſed, whereof <hi>France</hi> is too much a Maſter, that will occaſion the Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152962:22"/>of <hi>Cologns</hi> Repentance, at leaſt that of his Succeſſor after him, in caſe they begin to waver: Men were in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe at that time concerning who ſhould ſucceed him; for <hi>France</hi> ſaw at a diſtance, and ſhe ſuppoſed by all that had paſt, that ſhe might be able to prevail with the Chapter of <hi>Liege,</hi> to confer the Coadjutorſhip of the Principality and Biſhoprick of <hi>Liege</hi> upon Cardinal <hi>Furſtenburg;</hi> but thoſe that compoſed the Chapter better adviſed than any one durſt have believed or hoped for, had no mind to ſwallow the bait, but laught at it, which made him have recourſe to the Chapter of <hi>Cologne,</hi> where he hath had better ſucceſs, and notwithſtanding all the oppoſition the Pope and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour made; they went farther, and the Cardinal hath obtained what <hi>France</hi> demanded: They have been long about this buſineſs, and immediately upon Mens ſaying, That the Cannons knew what Gold was. <hi>France</hi> progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticated nothing but good to her ſelf, and found the Road to <hi>Cologne</hi> eaſier than to <hi>Munſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>France</hi> and the Cardinal know very well that the Pope will not give his Bull for it; but they may have the ſame comfort in that as they had for <hi>Munſter,</hi> they will do well enough without it, no body beſides being capable of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to it; and as I told you the Pope being aged, may chance to dye, and another more eaſie Man may ſucceed him.</p>
               <p>Now then by what we ſee come to paſs by the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Policy of <hi>France:</hi> Have I not great reaſon to ſay that the whole Empire, Electors, and other Kings, Princes, and States have great cauſe to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the deſigns of <hi>Leuis</hi> XIV. to prevent his riſing to an Empire for fear of becoming his Slaves, whereas at preſent he takes ſpecial care of ſome, and careſſes them; he will then Lord it over them, he will put off the Foxes skin, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152962:22"/>put on the Lyons again; they'l talk of nothing then, but of <hi>tel eſt mon bon plaiſir,</hi> ſuch my Will and Pleaſure is. Nothing but a Peace with the <hi>Turk</hi> can hinder him from growing Great; nothing but that can put the Emperour in a condition to oppoſe it. The King will be very cautious how he makes his limits at <hi>Ratisbon,</hi> during theſe Conteſts that give him an opportunity to build Fortreſſes, to defend what he ſhall uſurp; as we ſee he hath done but too much already: It will be requiſite to have an Army to drive him out thence. Have not we ſeen in the time of peace what the Spirit of <hi>France</hi> is capable of doing: 'Tis known, that amongſt other good qualities, he is indued with the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable gift of Uſurping well, finds always reaſons for the doing ſo; which he would have all Men receive for Articles of their Creed, as well as the juſt pretentions of the King upon the Empire, treated at large in a little Book, wherein the Wit of one called <hi>Aubri</hi> (Advocate in the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi>) hath been exerciſed? But the King of <hi>France</hi> his Manifeſto publiſhed newly at <hi>Ratis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone</hi> and other States of the Empire, to maintain the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Fortification of <hi>Tarbrack,</hi> deſerves to be inſerted in this Book, to let theſe who have not yet ſeen it, underſtand the ſlender Reaſons he alledges to palliate his infraction of the laſt Truce. Behold here what his Miniſter hath-publiſhed to all the World.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The King having been informed of the complaints which the Miniſters of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> make upon the account of ſome outrages committed at <hi>Tarbrack</hi> by his Majeſties Order, who throughout the Empire they charge with acting contrary, and call him an infringer of the Treaty concluded in the Year of our Lord, 1684.</q> The which hath obliged his ſaid Majeſty to iſſue out Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the Count <hi>de Crecy,</hi> his Envoy Extraordinary, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152962:23"/>Plenipotentiary at the Imperial Diet at <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Miniſters of the Electors, Princes, and States of the Empire aſſembled in the ſaid place, the ſmall ground there is for ſuch a complaint in it ſelf, and the juſt occaſions they adminiſter to all thoſe who have a deſire to preſerve the publick peace; to believe that this is a pretence that they are willing to make uſe of to diſturb the ſame peace and quiet.</p>
               <p>Firſt of all, If it may be ſaid upon good grounds that that Treaty ratified at <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> may not properly be called a Truce, its true definition being only a forbearance or ſufferance, by vertue of which (although the War be ſtill in being) we are to forbear all Acts of Hoſtility; there being at that time no rupture between <hi>France</hi> and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; this tolleration may be lookt upon as a mutual promiſe of a good underſtanding and Union for the ſpace of Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years; in conſideration whereof the Emperour and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire on the one part, are to lay aſide, during the ſaid term, their Soveraignty, Rights, Superiority, and Protection, or all other pretences whatſoever they may have upon Lands, Places, or Towns fallen to <hi>France</hi> before the firſt of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1681. His Majeſty in like manner binds himſelf not to make any farther ſuit or proſecution in the Empire during the ſaid time. Theſe are the moſt material Covenants, by which they interchangeably aſſure each other of a long continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Friendſhip and good Intelligence; which afforded means to the Emperours Arme is to conquer all <hi>Hungary,</hi> and to put themſelves and Empire in a poſture, and in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to undertake a War, which otherwiſe would not have waged but at great coſt and charges; and peradventure at the hazard and ruine of the Electors, Princes, and States of the Empire. But further to demonſtrate this weak pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, altogether not to be tenible, nor can hold Water of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152962:23"/>it ſelf, we need not run over the Articles of this Treaty, and though we might even look upon it as a Treaty barely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded only for the ſecurity of the tranquillity of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and to procure for it the means whereby to imploy its Armies againſt the common Enemy; yet one cannot for all that prove that it may deprive the King of his Power to fortifie thoſe places where his Majeſty hath right ſo to do, as well by the poſſeſſion he hath already had, as by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent of the Empire, granted by vertue of the ſame Treaty, nor that he cannot act in thoſe places as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; you need only peruſe all the Treaties of Truce which have been made hitherto, to ſee whether a prohibition of fortifying is not expreſly included therein at ſuch time as both Parties cannot agree. By this toleration of the Truce of <hi>Bonviſe</hi> in the year of our Lord 1537, 'tis ſaid, that whilſt the Ceſſation of Arms laſts in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> King <hi>Francis</hi> I. could not ſend any Forces into the County of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> nor there raiſe any Fortification: This Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gives us ſufficiently to underſtand, that the King was impowered to fortifie his places thereabouts, and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, during the ſaid Truce; ſo that they were bound to inſert a clauſe into this Treaty, to deprive <hi>France</hi> of this Liberty in the County of St. <hi>Paul</hi> only.</p>
               <p>The General Truce that was agreed upon at <hi>Nice,</hi> in the Year 1538, ratifies and confirms this ſame Article concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning St. <hi>Paul,</hi> but it doth no way hinder the two Princes to cauſe Fortifications to be raiſed any where elſe.</p>
               <p>The Ceſſation made in 1555, makes no mention of this point, but the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Netherlands</hi> upon their concluding a Truce in 1609, having a mind indeed to deprive each other of having the liberty of raiſing any new Fortreſs in the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> inſerted this Clauſe; <hi>There ſhall be on neither ſide any
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152962:24"/>Fortreſs in the</hi> Low Countreys <hi>during the Ceſſation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Peace was in agitation at <hi>Munſter</hi> between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> that they demurr'd longeſt upon and proved the greateſt obſtacle to the concluſion, was, that the Catholick King could not find in his heart to quit his claim to <hi>Catalonia,</hi> which cauſed them to agree upon a Truce for Thirty years for that Province alone; during which term both Kings ſhould keep what he poſſeſt at that time; but another difficulty emerg'd that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> could not endure that they ſhould fortifie during the Truce; thoſe places in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> to which the <hi>French</hi> would not agree, alledging it unjuſt, upon this account that thereby this would put them in a poſture of being Defendants only, and not Aggreſſors, which was permitted in all Ages, they would not ſo much as admit of the Expedient offered by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of the <hi>States General.</hi> The ſame caſe ſtands good now, as to the preſent Treaty. Every one knows that the prohibitions to raiſe Fortifications propounded by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Empire, in the Ninth and Tenth Articles of the ſame project of the Empire, and what was then and there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchangeably delivered by publick Writing, was interjected by <hi>France:</hi> Beſides, the Imperial Miniſters would by no means give their conſent that the Emperour ſhould yield up to the King ſuch places whereof he was in preſent poſſeſſion, which his Majeſty would not have medled with, nor limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor encroached upon. The Emperours Miniſters not able to make good this demand, gave it over. 'Tis hard to believe that the Imperial Miniſters will draw any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be a ſufficient ground of complaint from the Eighth and Ninth Article of the Truce; foraſmuch as the former contains only the ſettling the Lands upon the Proprietors again, who would take the Oath of Allegiance for them: The Soveraignty whereof was delivered to his Majeſty. The other is, that his ſaid Majeſty ſhall permit the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152962:24"/>to have the free Exerciſe of their Religion. Moreover the re-union of <hi>Tarbrack</hi> having been irrecoverably ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged by a decree of the Royal Chamber of <hi>Metz</hi> in the Month of <hi>April,</hi> 1681. It is hard to conceive what Title the Imperial Miniſters can pretend to in accuſing <hi>France</hi> of acting contrary to the Ceſſation of Arms, eſpecially the King giving viſible and dayly demonſtrations of the inviolable Obſervation of the leaſt punctillio of them, helping and furthering what in him lies, the progreſs of the Imperial Forces againſt thoſe <hi>Barbarians</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> through his moderation and complyance, and what adminiſters ground of ſuſpition concerning the deſigns of the Court at <hi>Vienna,</hi> (which his Miniſters do but too much lay open upon all occaſions) is their not being deſirous of keeping the Truce any longer than they may be ſtrong enough to break it.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all this, conſidering that this Truce hath offered to Chriſtendom that happy Peace and Tranquillity it enjoys at this day; and hath ſupplyed means to the States and Circles of the Empire by their aſſiſtance to bring upon the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire all thoſe miſchiefs wherewith they threatned the Hereditary Countreys. We dare boldly and truly ſay, that the Emperour is beholding to him for the preſervation of his Country, and for all thoſe advantages he hath had over the <hi>Turks:</hi> His Miniſters are as much to blame to complain that the King making uſe of his full power, hath cauſed his frontier places to be fortified, as ſtanding in moſt need: Juſt as a Soveraign, for the ſecurity, repoſe, and proſperity of his Subjects, cauſeth the bounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his Territories to be fortified; would, not by ſo doing, make us believe, that he had the leaſt thought of ſiezing upon his Neighbours Countrey, or any mind to Commence a War, no more than any private Perſon buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf in repairing the utmoſt Fences of his Lands to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152962:25"/>make them good, would thereby give but ſmall proof of his deſire to entrench upon his Neighbours. But yet his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty is not without hope but that the Wiſdom and Prudence of the States of the Empire aſſembled at <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly reflect upon the juſt ſuſpitions which the ill-groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded complaints of the Imperial Miniſters have occaſioned to him, and that they will bethink themſelves of one way or other that the good Intelligence which his Majeſty purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to maintain with the Empire, may not be interrupted, nor impeded. <hi>Given at</hi> Fountainbleau, Octob. 22th 1687.</p>
               <p>To hear this Manifeſto, would not a Man judge that the Emperour is obliged to the King for all his Victories over the <hi>Turk,</hi> and without him the Empire had been quite loſt, when all the World ſees evidently by what we have ſaid, that it was none but he that induced the Grand Seigniour to break the Truce, and to ſend relief to <hi>Tekely;</hi> but the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>France</hi> is always deceitful.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Policy of <hi>France,</hi> and the Maxims, in relation to <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom the Empire I paſs to <hi>Spain,</hi> which Kingdom and <hi>France</hi> have divided <hi>Europe</hi> between them ſome years laſt paſt; all other Princes have liſted themſelves under their Banner; thereafter as their Intereſt required, but the moſt part agreed in that point to ſupport the weaker, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a juſt ballance between them. The late Mounſieur <hi>Sully,</hi> in a Letter to <hi>Henry</hi> IV. concerning the Quarrel with <hi>Spain,</hi> ſays that the leaſt growth of Power in the one is lookt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152962:25"/>upon to be a weakning and leſſening of the other. Until <hi>Philip</hi> IV. time, <hi>Spain</hi> ever kept up its head, (though it began to decline in <hi>Philip</hi> the Seconds, by reaſon of the War in the <hi>Low Countreys</hi>) but ever ſince that, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly after the laſt King <hi>Philip</hi> IV. Death, <hi>France</hi> got the upper hand, and <hi>Spain</hi> humbly ſubmitted.</p>
               <p>Upon the Feſtival of one of the Kings of <hi>Spain</hi> who was Sainted, the Preacher St. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> extolling the grandeur of his Mighty King in his Sermon, told 'em, that if his God was not God, the King <hi>Don Philip</hi> ſhould be God; but I ſuppoſe ſomething leſs than ſo, would ſatisfie his Succeſſor, the caſe being altered ſince that. And yet <hi>Charles</hi> II. is King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſtill, has the ſame <hi>Indies,</hi> and his Ships go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and come home laden with Gold and Silver as they us't to do heretofore; but ſtill this <hi>Spain</hi> is not like that, which was once the Terrour of all Princes in <hi>Europe,</hi> who were but juſtly jealous of her aſpiring Greatneſs, and had reaſon to be Confederates againſt it for their common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: Now 'tis in the ſame condition that a Thief is, when he's brought to his laſt ſhifts, and juſt ready to be taken.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Spain</hi> were not ſupported by its Allies, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. King of <hi>France</hi> would quickly be at <hi>Madrid:</hi> The <hi>Low Countries</hi> would bend under the <hi>French</hi> yoak, in leſs than one Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign, though 'twould be effected more eaſily, becauſe their own Prince has no Children, and is very ſickly, and though they ſee utter ruine coming upon them, yet they dare make no oppoſition, for they could only make ſport for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent <hi>French</hi> Troops if they ſhould, having no proſpect of ſuccours from any body that's able to reſcue them. <hi>France</hi> knows all this well enough, and 'tis very true, that <hi>France</hi> waits only for a fit opportunity to take poſſeſſion of the Queens Right in the Dauphin's Name, for the Crown of <hi>Spain</hi> falls to the Female Sex, and it came to the Houſe of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152962:26"/>
                  <hi>Auſtria</hi> by a Woman, that is to ſay, by <hi>Jane, Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Spains</hi> Daughter, who married a Prince of that Family.</p>
               <p>To let you ſee how much <hi>Spain</hi> ſuffers it ſelf to be <hi>baffled</hi> by <hi>France,</hi> I need only ſhew you two Examples, which will convince you that I have ſaid nothing but what is true. The King of <hi>France</hi> ſent a Memorial to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and to the States of the United Provinces, to this effect: That if the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould grant the <hi>Low Countreys</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> or but make him Governour (as the report was when he married the Arch-dutcheſs) that ſhe would then without more ado break off the peace, ſince neither of thoſe things could be done without manifeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to the Dauphin's Right. Mr. <hi>Feuquier</hi> was the Man who gave the Memorial to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and Count <hi>D'avaux</hi> to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces;</hi> but were <hi>Paris</hi> over this, perhaps you'l ſay, that <hi>Spain</hi> did not conſider it well, and they are ſo juſtly afraid of <hi>France,</hi> that it is no wonder if that puts 'em a little out of their Wits: But I am going to tell you a thing, which you'l own does ſufficiently diſcover the weakneſs and poor Spirit of <hi>Spain;</hi> it hapned at the Ceremony of making an Entry into <hi>London,</hi> that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadors met: The Baron <hi>Watville</hi> went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Mounſieur d' Eſtrade, France</hi> preſently complains of this indignity; and <hi>Spain</hi> was ſo pitifully mean, as to diſown that brave Action of their Ambaſſador: Thus by that ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous procedure <hi>Spain</hi> ſuffered in its Honour, and gave place to <hi>France,</hi> though there was nothing like neceſſity for their doing it: I can ſee no other reaſon for't, but fear of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law,</hi> and dread of the Troops which <hi>France</hi> keeps up to inforce its Commands, which are juſt ready too, in caſe the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould dye ſuddenly. Let <hi>Charles</hi> II. take what care he can in ſettling the Succeſſion, if he has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152962:26"/>for his own Family, and the laſt Will and intent of <hi>Philip</hi> IV. his Succeſſor will have enough to do, and a ſcurvy War to maintain. The Queen, who is altogether <hi>French</hi> both by her Birth and Inclinations, has her Faction in the Kingdom, and when the King is dead, will much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truſt her <hi>Couzen-Germain,</hi> than a Prince who is a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, at leaſt would be ſo, were it not for the Marriage, which will be a great ſtrengthning to his Party. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of the <hi>Infanta's</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> with Kings of <hi>France,</hi> have ever been the cauſe of great differences between the two Crowns, and very fatal to <hi>Spain;</hi> but the Marriage of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Thereſia</hi> with <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. compleats the miſery which is inevitably falling upon <hi>Spain,</hi> and how ſtifly ſoever the King of <hi>France</hi> may have denyed his deſigns, yet he never inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to keep either his Word or Oath as to that matter. We are ſufficiently ſatisfied by the obſtacles he puts, that the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty may not be regiſtred in Parliament; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by his Manifeſto's (which have run all the World over) of the Queen of <hi>France</hi>'s <hi>Juſt Pretentions.</hi> What good can <hi>Spain</hi> get by Marriages and Alliances with <hi>France?</hi> On the contrary very great Miſchief, for 'tis by reaſon of the laſt Marriage that <hi>France</hi> layes claim to all this, the wiſer <hi>Philip</hi> II. preferr'd the Arch-Duke <hi>Erneſt,</hi> and afterward <hi>Albert.</hi> The Truce which <hi>France</hi> has now made, is deſign'd only to amuze and lull <hi>Spain</hi> and its Allies aſleep: Thus to make them lay down their Arms, and in the mean time the <hi>French</hi> King has at leaſt a Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Men a foot, who dance up and down, ſometimes towards <hi>Alſace,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time toward <hi>Cologne,</hi> and pretty often toward the <hi>Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries:</hi> All this is only to make them us'd to him, that ſo they may think he has no deſign upon them, and lay by all jealouſie and ſuſpition. But when he finds a good op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, you ſhall ſee him fall upon them, as a Hawk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152962:27"/>her quarry, and carry them off too if he pleaſes; for what ſhould hinder him, when there's not a Man in Arms, and by that time the Allies can be prepared, the King of <hi>France</hi> has done his buſineſs. Thus this Truce is only to bear in hand, and amuze the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> that they may not make War upon him, and that he may be conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a condition to take poſſeſſion of the <hi>Dauphins Right</hi> ſo ſoon as ever the King of <hi>Spain</hi> is dead, without any other legal Proceſs, but that of <hi>Dragoon Law:</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> will find themſelves miſerably deluded in relying upon this Truce. 'Tis <hi>a broken reed which will pierce through their hands,</hi> and if unhappily, the Emperour ſhould be ſtill ingaged in a War with the <hi>Turks,</hi> what ſhould hinder the two <hi>French</hi> Armies, the one in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> the other in the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> from being Maſters of all where they go. I know very well that the Intereſt of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> are both concern'd to defend the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> as the ſequel will ſhew us: But in the one the <hi>French</hi> have ſo true a Friend, (who has ſo much buſineſs beſide upon his hands at home) that he will concern himſelf no more for the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> than his Predeceſſor did for <hi>Luxemburg.</hi> As for the <hi>States</hi> they have but Men enough to defend their own Country, and are naturally very good Husbands: As for <hi>Cologne</hi> and <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> his Majeſty will probably put ſome Men into their Towns for them, as he has done heretofore.</p>
               <p>I think it a vaſt miſtake in the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> to ſend Men into the <hi>Low Countreys</hi> for Governours (who for the moſt part) go thither only to fill their Purſe, as the ſaying is, and ſo return; and to do this effectually, they don't ſcruple to rob both King and Countrey, pay neither Landlords nor Men, which makes them deſert, ſo that inſtead of One Thouſand Men in a Regiment, perhaps there is Fifty; and once I ſaw a whole Regiment which was going to change Garriſon,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152962:27"/>carried in a Waggon. In ſhort, a Man need only to have been once in <hi>Flanders,</hi> to ſee this that I tell you, the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers upon the Guard hold out their Hats to you for an Alms, and the very Officers are fain to live with the Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins upon the Alms which the good Men beg.</p>
               <p>The three laſt <hi>Iriſh</hi> Regiments which the King of <hi>England</hi> granted the King of <hi>Spain</hi> for the ſervice of the <hi>Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries</hi> which were effectually raiſed, are waſted like Snow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sun, and now I don't believe there's Fifty Men left. <hi>Spain</hi> in my poor judgment is very much in the wrong for another thing, that is, to rely upon its Allies for the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and upon that ſcore to neglect ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what Men are requiſite for the Countreys ſecurity: Beſides, they may be ſure that <hi>France,</hi> knowing the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Governours ſo very well, do often feel their Pulſe, and takes advantage of their weakneſs: Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Men will never be beat out on't, but that the Marquis of <hi>Grana</hi> was made a Tool, and put a helping hand to the taking of <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> the thing is as clear as the Sun at Noon-day; Four or Five Millions which he has left behind him are a ſhrewd ſign of it: I tell you no improbable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and nothing but what happens every day; there are very few Men in our Age, who are proof againſt a Million of Money; I confeſs there are ſome, but you muſt grant me they are very rare: The <hi>Low Countreys</hi> are no Inheritance to the Governours, ſo that they get all they can out of it, as if they hired it. I wont ſay that all who come there are of the ſame ſtamp (God forbid) 'twould be ſad indeed if <hi>Spain</hi> had no Subjects that were honeſt; but 'tis very certain that for theſe laſt Ages, <hi>France</hi> has <hi>gallanted</hi> the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and thinks them highly obliged, if not depending upon her. There's no trick which the <hi>French</hi> craft does not uſe to bring about their deſigns, for they have ever found that little
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152962:28"/>Countrey, a hard bone to pick, but their preſent King has given it deviliſh bites theſe years laſt paſt; <hi>France</hi> knows very well, too, that if they were once Maſters of it, they might then bend all their ſtrength toward <hi>Catalonia</hi> and <hi>Rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillon,</hi> and having nothing left to fear or quarrel about in that Countrey, march on quickly to <hi>Madrid,</hi> which is no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult matter when they have once made themſelves Maſters of ſome of the Frontiers to go in and out at. 'Tis for this reaſon that the Councils of <hi>Spain</hi> conſidering the ſtrength of <hi>France,</hi> ſhould take other meaſures than they do for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and I ſee but one only expedient in the poſture that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Affairs are in at preſent, which can give them preſent eaſe, except they had rather have that Countrey fall into the <hi>French</hi> hands, as without doubt it muſt, if they don't prevent it ſpeedily. It is certain, that nothing but an Army with a good General can prevent the ruine which is falling upon their heads. We ſee after what faſhion the Men, who are there now are paid; and the inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble number of them, and to ſay the truth, there ought to be Twenty Thouſand effective Men (beſide what is there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, in Garriſon to ſecure the Countrey, and Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand more, in caſe of a Rupture; and ſince <hi>Spain</hi> can't fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them with ſo many Men: You muſt let the Towns there levy Men, and pay them who will be willing to do it, to ſecure themſelves, and avoi'd falling under the barbarous Dominion of the <hi>French,</hi> or be quite ruin'd perhaps, before it comes to that, as many Towns and Cities have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and that flat Country now of late, in which the moſt Religious places were not ſpared. I know very well that that propoſal has been debated in Council long ſince, and that the Council of <hi>Spain</hi> has ever rejected it for ſlight rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. A good careful Governour, eſpecially the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who is ſo brave a Commander, and adorn'd with
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152962:28"/>Conqueſts at the head of Forty Thouſand Men ſupported by the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> would make <hi>France</hi> ſhake. <hi>France</hi> has its Emiſſaries in the Council at <hi>Madrid,</hi> as well as at other places, to oppoſe every thing which may poſſibly thwart her deſigns; and I am of opinion that it will turn to better account for the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to ſecure his <hi>Low Countries</hi> with the help of a Militi a payd by the Cities (who wont abuſe him) than to loſe that Countrey for want of Men to defend it: The latter of theſe is almoſt irretrieva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but that former would be effectual, were it not for an ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded Jealouſie, which poſſibly heretofore might have deſerved conſideration, but is now quite out of doors, for in my judgment we ought ever to take in hand the thing which is moſt urgent, when the one is inevitable, and the other may probably never come to paſs. I ſay once more, that <hi>France</hi> can never compaſs her great deſign, but by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt of all Maſter of the <hi>Low Countreys:</hi> 'Twas for this reaſon that <hi>Du Pleſſis</hi> adviſed his Maſter to ſet upon it that way; and 'tis that paſs alone which <hi>Spain</hi> and its Allies ought neceſſarily to ſtop with the ſame care and diligence, as they would the breach in a Bank, through which the raging Sea is ready to come in upon them, and this we ſhall ſee hereafter.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> Kings Ambition and Intereſt is a Torrent, whoſe Impetuoſity neither Affinity of Blood, nor Alliance, Peace, Treaties, Truce, Swearing, nor even Mutual Oaths are able to withſtand: I'le go farther, no not the very bounds which God by his wiſe Providence has ſet to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of every Monarchy, which ſeems to ſpeak to each Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, <hi>Hither ſhalt thou go, and no farther.</hi> But <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. has ſworn not to reſt ſatisfied with the Lot which the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Monarch of the Univerſe has given him. Who can tell, had he once Conquered the World, but he would
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152962:29"/>begin again another <hi>Tower of Babel,</hi> to ſcale the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens? Ambition knows no bounds, but <hi>Pride goes before a fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh that <hi>Spain</hi> would not ſuffer her ſelf to be lull'd aſleep by this deceitful Truce! 'Tis a <hi>Dalilah,</hi> which all on a ſudden cry out to the <hi>Spaniards, the Philiſtians are upon thee:</hi> But I am afraid it will be ſo as 'twas with <hi>Sampſon,</hi> who when he awoke, finding himſelf faſt bound, could no longer avoid becoming a Prey and Conqueſt to his Enemy. The <hi>Grandees</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> are a great help to <hi>France,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute (without dreaming on't) very much to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of her Intereſt, and ſupport of her Ambition, whil'ſt they inrich themſelves at their Maſters Expence, and in the mean time diſable him to keep up Men for their common defence; but if they were well adviſed, they ſhould reflect ſeriouſly upon the Condition they are in at preſent, and upon that they are like to be in when they fall under the Tyranny of <hi>France:</hi> How happily would ſuch a compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon obviate the miſery which is coming upon them? For they muſt think when a <hi>French</hi> Man comes to the Crown, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> will be but little conſidered, and at beſt be only pittied or deſpiſed: The natural antipathy between thoſe two Nations wont ſuffer the new King to truſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with them, and all their ſtatelineſs will ſerve only for the <hi>French</hi> Court to laugh and jeer at.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> muſt not flatter themſelves if that comes to paſs, that the Dauphin after his Fathers Death, will leave <hi>France</hi> to go and live in <hi>Spain:</hi> The King's of <hi>France</hi> will alway value <hi>Verſailles</hi> beyond the fineſt City in <hi>Spain:</hi> They will ſend Vice-Roys thither who ſhall be <hi>Frenchmen</hi> both by nature and diſpoſition, Mortal Enemies to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that thus they may be ſecure that they wont join in any thing with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> againſt the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt. Theſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152962:29"/>and Vice-Roys will bring along with them, for their neceſſary uſe their <hi>French</hi> Tax, the <hi>Mal tote,</hi> which will in a little time bring forth a whole ſwarm of Impoſitions, as the <hi>Taille Taillon Aide, Grant,</hi> or <hi>Octroit, Preciput, Equivalent, Free Gift, Gratification, Aid</hi> upon <hi>Wines, Gabels</hi> upon <hi>Salt, Corn</hi> and <hi>Flower, Tobacco</hi> and <hi>Perriwigs,</hi> on all ſorts of <hi>Stuffs, Linnen-cloth, Le pied fourchu,</hi> Impoſt upon <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the Mark of <hi>Paper,</hi> upon <hi>Silver</hi> and <hi>Tin,</hi> upon <hi>Milled</hi> and <hi>Silk Stockings,</hi> Impoſt upon <hi>Ice, Controlle des Exploits,</hi> Tax upon <hi>Fee-Farms,</hi> Tax upon the <hi>New Conqueſts, Quint</hi> and <hi>Requint, Mortmains,</hi> the price of Valuations, the Mark of Gold, the two <hi>Sols</hi> a pound, the right of Sealage, right of <hi>Controlle,</hi> of Regiſter and Oath, <hi>La Paulette,</hi> abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Wages, Cuſtom, appointment of a Governour, the Eighth Peny, Impoſt and the re-union to the Crown of whatſoever hath been given or ſold, with ſome others not worth naming. Again, after that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would have for their hoſts ſome of thoſe Deviliſh Farmers of the Kings Revenue who would faſten upon them, as if they were a Conquered Countrey, and at firſt daſh would lay a Tax upon the Sun, knowing they make uſe of that inſtead of a Fagot.</p>
               <p>Therefore I maintain that <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould endeavour above all things, to diſpoſe the Emperor to accept of a Peace, or at leaſt a Truce with the Grand Seignior: To look out while this preſent King is living, for a Prince to ſucceed him, and that this Prince may betake himſelf in time to <hi>Madrid</hi> to be well known to the people, and be in the Heart of the Kingdom; To Defend it, and get Crown'd immediately upon the Kings Death: To poſſeſs himſelf of the great Seal, and all Inſtruments relating to the Crown: And to make the Grandees of <hi>Spain</hi> ſide with him as their Lord and Maſter.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:152962:30"/>
               <p>Moreover by this means <hi>Spain</hi> may make an early provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the ſecurity of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and be juſtly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceived in that pernicious Opinion which the Council of <hi>Spain</hi> has, that <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> muſt neceſſarily defend them for their own Intereſt. I own 'tis true, they ought to do it; but if <hi>France</hi> looſes <hi>England</hi> from her true Intereſt, and diverts her from thinking ſo (as without doubt we ſhall find) if this comes to paſs in any reaſonable time, the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> whatever good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and whatever intereſt they may have in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> 'twont be in their power to ſtop the fury of the <hi>French,</hi> which like an impetuous Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent will in a moment ſweep away the beſt part of <hi>Flanders.</hi> So that <hi>Spain</hi> ought to think of this in good earneſt; and not lye aſleep whilſt the <hi>French</hi> policy is ſo active, and is preparing long before-hand for ſo important an Affair which will never be offered them again, if they let ſlip the opportunity of being Maſters of it. <hi>France</hi> takes all ways imaginable to get one, and makes it her whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; it behooves <hi>Spain</hi> to do ſo too, if ſhe would avoid Ruine and not fall under the Yoke of <hi>France,</hi> which is the greateſt plague that can be ſent upon her, no leſs than the Deſtruction and Deſolation of her people, the expoſing and humbling all the Grandees of <hi>Spain,</hi> who will be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to give place to the meaneſt <hi>French</hi> Gentleman. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the <hi>Spaniards</hi> are well advis'd, after the Death of their King, they ought not to ſuffer the Monarchy to go to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. but with the laſt drop of their Blood; and Baniſh for ever this Violent, Inſolent Spirit of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:152962:30"/>
               <head>The Policy of <hi>France</hi> and her Maximes in Reference to <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEnry</hi> VIII. King of <hi>England</hi> in his time made a Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Medal, on which was Engraven a Hand coming out of the Clouds, holding a pair of Scales equally poiſed, the one Scale denoting <hi>Spain,</hi> and the other <hi>France,</hi> with a motto in <hi>Latin,</hi> to this purpoſe in <hi>Engliſh, I throw the Scales on that ſide I give my Friendſhip.</hi> Without doubt that Prince knew his power, but now I can compare <hi>England</hi> to nothing but an Ox, which knows not his own ſtrength and ſuffers himſelf tamely to be yok'd. That Kingdom has this great advantage, that it Guards it ſelf, and an Enemy can't invade it but with vaſt difficulty. 'Tis not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded without going often to and fro upon the Sea, they'l have Wind and Water to fight againſt, and a powerful Fleet to engage with before they ſet foot aſhore: Inſomuch that if the King of <hi>England</hi> be at peace with <hi>Holland,</hi> 'tis undeniable in his power to make the Victory lean to that ſide he is of: <hi>France</hi> has found this ſo true, (although there is a perfect Hatred and Antipathy between thoſe two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) that ſhe has ſpared no Coſt, and compaſſes Sea and Land to withdraw <hi>England</hi> from its true laſting intereſt, and bring her over to their ſide, or at leaſt make her ſtand <hi>Neuter,</hi> and look on with arms-acroſs, while the King of <hi>France</hi> Acts his Tragedy upon the Theatre of <hi>Europe.</hi> In the mean time tis moſt certain that <hi>England</hi> can reſcue this ſame <hi>Europe</hi> from being enſlaved to <hi>France,</hi> better than any other Nation, if ſhe pleaſes.</p>
               <p>If the King of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> did but know his own Strength and Real Intereſt, he might be not only the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152962:31"/>and Umpire of the World, But might make Peace, when he pleaſes, between all the Chriſtian Princes.</p>
               <p>There are but two things requiſite to effect this, both which are very eaſie, nay are in the Kings power whenever he has a mind to't.</p>
               <p>The Firſt is, That the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> take Care to be alwayes beloved by his People, and that there be a good underſtanding between him and his Parliament.</p>
               <p>The Second is, To have a ſtrict Alliance with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited-Provinces,</hi> and live in perfect Amity with them, and maintain inviolably this Union and Correſpondence in all that Concerns each other. The former of theſe is mighty eaſily done, and the King will obtain it effectually, when he once reſolves to Require nothing of his Parliament but what is agreeable to the Laws of the Realm, as he already promis'd in his Coronation Oath. The latter will be done ſo ſoon as His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> leaves liſtening to the <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries, and puts out of his head all Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Surmiſes which thoſe Creatures continually try to poſſeſs him with, having nothing that he need be afraid of from the <hi>States,</hi> who don't wiſh to <hi>Aggrandize</hi> themſelves, and Uſurp their Neighbours Territories as <hi>France</hi> do's; but only keep what God has given them, and be able to protect their Countrey in the enjoyment of that Liberty they have at preſent. <hi>France,</hi> who is ſatisfied of the Truth of what I have ſaid, takes all occaſions to obſtruct it; She is never without ſome of thoſe Helliſh Reſtleſs Spirits in the Kingdom, to ſow the <hi>Tares</hi> of miſ-underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings between the King and his Parliament. Ever ſince the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have appeared to be <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> this <hi>Catholicon</hi> has wrought well, and <hi>the Spirit of France</hi> has been at work to ſet the Epiſcopal Party againſt the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian,</hi> and to inſinuate into the Minds of the latter, that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152962:31"/>the Biſhops were inclined to <hi>Popery,</hi> and that moſt of them were Jeſuites in Biſhops Cloaths, Who would certainly ſeduce the people little by little, and be <hi>Turn Coates</hi> ſo ſoon as they have a good Opportunity, and dare diſcover their Opinion: That the King himſelf was Popiſhly-affected, and a thouſand things of this nature, which exaſperated the people, and made his Parliament jealous of him, for which reaſon they Granted nothing at all, or but very little of what the King ask't, and by this means his own private Occaſions grew ſo very urgent that he neglected the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, twas <hi>France</hi> which kindled the firſt Sparks of the Civil War, which cauſed ſo much Bloodſhed both to King and People; inſomuch that when the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſador return'd home from <hi>England,</hi> he boaſted how he had kindled a fire which would not be <hi>put out</hi> a good while, and that for <hi>one twenty years England</hi> ſhould not be in a Condition to do <hi>France</hi> any harm. One <hi>Father Joſeph</hi> a <hi>Capuchin</hi> was inſtrumental in <hi>fomenting</hi> the Diviſion among the Catholicks under-hand, and I can aſſure you there were ſome of thoſe Catholicks in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Army: King <hi>Charles</hi> himſelf affirms it, and tells you that the Rebellion among them proceeded from his having denied them places, and as ſoon as War was declared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and Parliament, the King of <hi>France</hi> ſent <hi>Cromwel</hi> Six Hundred Thouſand <hi>Livres</hi> to pay his Army at the beginning. This is publickly known, and all who liv'd in that Age know it to be true. But at preſent the King of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> having chang'd his Religion, <hi>France</hi> has chang'd her Battery too, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> is now her main <hi>Piece of Ordinance:</hi> The people are ſo exaſperated againſt each other, that his Majeſty of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> muſt think of little elſe this good while, and will find work enough in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152962:32"/>his Kingdom to compaſs his Ends (even though he had got a Parliament at his Devotion) and if he ſhould live Twenty years longer he would ſcarce ſee a Concluſion, but muſt be fain to leave that buſineſs for his Succeſſour. So that the King had need ſtand upon his Guard, while the people are thus diſ-affected; He not being in a Condition to ſend his Army abroad, nor having Money to maintain them, <hi>France</hi> in the mean time may do what ſhe pleaſes, may take the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and all <hi>Spain</hi> too if the King of <hi>Spain</hi> happens to dye, which is the thing <hi>France</hi> waits for ſo impatiently.</p>
               <p>For the Second thing, which is an Alliance with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> and a perfect Harmony and Agreement between thoſe two Potentates, to oppoſe all Kings or Princes whatever, who ſhall offer to violate the peace of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> 'Tis an undoubted Truth that the <hi>States</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it of all things, provided it be done ſo ſecurely as they may venture to rely upon it, and be back't upon occaſion. Of which there is ſmall likelihood ſo long as things are as they are in <hi>England.</hi> This is what <hi>France</hi> would not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſee, ſince the joyning of theſe two powers would probably divert her from many Enterprizes, and make her loſe her longing to undertake any thing contrary to the late Treaties of peace at <hi>Nimeghen</hi> and the Truce: But <hi>France</hi> takes Care to hinder this, and the miſtruſt and jealouſie which ſhe keeps afoot in <hi>England</hi> like magnifying Glaſſes, makes the trivialleſt Objects look greater than they are, both in publick and private Affairs: We need go no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the buſineſs of <hi>Bantam,</hi> which might long ago have been accommodated, but <hi>France</hi> thinks it more uſeful to her, that things be let alone as they are, and neither go forward nor backward, for fear of a happy Reſult. An Union of <hi>England</hi> with the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> would give
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152962:32"/>no great encouragement to the <hi>French</hi> deſigns upon the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Netherlands,</hi> for if <hi>England</hi> were ſo minded, the King of <hi>France</hi> could never do any good, if the late King would but have ſeemed to have ſtir'd, the <hi>French</hi> had never taken <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> but they knew his weakneſs, and were ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to blind him, that he good Prince, never ſaw the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief on't till after the City was taken.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>England</hi> acted very much againſt her own Intereſt, when ſhe parted with <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> that City opened the Gate to go into <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries:</hi> But now 'twill be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if thoſe Countreys fall under the yoak of <hi>Lewis le Grand,</hi> and if he by his Conqueſts joins <hi>Neuport</hi> and <hi>Oſtend</hi> to <hi>Dunkirk: Fluſſing</hi> in a little time will be thought conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for him, and then he may very well begin to diſpute the Dominion of the Seas with <hi>England,</hi> and obſtruct her Commerce; and if at laſt the King of <hi>France</hi> Maſters <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which misfortune may happen, (the <hi>Low Countries</hi> being loſt) <hi>England</hi> may very well think 'tis her turn next. As 'twas for this Reaſon that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> told heretofore Mounſieur <hi>Sully</hi> the Moſt Chriſtian Kings Embaſſador, that neither <hi>France,</hi> nor <hi>England,</hi> nor any other Prince had any right to pretend to the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> and further, that ſhe would never ſuffer, that his King ſhould ſo much as think on't.</p>
               <p>This very <hi>Sully</hi> in a Letter to <hi>Henry</hi> IV. ſent him word, <hi>That with a great Army (for all what the Queen had ſaid) he might take a courſe to keep them in order, and take poſſeſſion of ſuch Lands and Cities in the Low Countries, as he ſhould think fit for his turn, and join</hi> France <hi>intirely with the</hi> United Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>which is the only means</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to reſtore</hi> France <hi>to its Antient ſplendour, and make her Superiour to all the reſt of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom: For if once by hook or by crook the Provinces of</hi> Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburg, Juliers, la Marck, Mons, Limburg, Aix, <hi>and</hi> Cleves
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152962:33"/>
                  <hi>were united to</hi> France, <hi>without doubt all the reſt of the Country would be forc't to follow their example, being ſeparated from any communication with the reſt of the World. France</hi> has been fixt that way ever ſince ſhe ſaw there was no good to be done towards <hi>Italy,</hi> but all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> are highly concerned to put a ſtop to that Conqueſt: And there are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe two Neighbouring Powers which are able, and whoſe Intereſt it is moſt, to hinder the progreſs that <hi>France</hi> makes in the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> which will draw after it, as I have ſaid before, dire effects: As for <hi>Spain</hi> of it ſelf, 'tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Body ſtanding aloof off from its Members, which has nothing left but her Tongue: She is reduc't ſo low, as even to ſay her Prayers to <hi>Notre Dame Charite,</hi> and to beg her good Maſters and Friends to take care of her, and not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake her: <hi>England</hi> can do much toward the preſerving the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and if her King had not promis't, to ſit ſtill, <hi>Luxemburg</hi> would have been at this time as 'twas before, a bone for <hi>France</hi> to pick. His Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty knows this very well, and 'tis for this reaſon that he takes ſo much pains to keep his <hi>Britanique</hi> Majeſty firm to his Intereſts, and if he wont declare for him, at leaſt that he will look on, and accept a neutrality. To bring this about, he ſpares nothing, neither Preſents, nor Penſion, nor Tricks; and I may ſafely ſay, that the Money which <hi>France</hi> gives, is a venomous Serpent, lurking under the Roſe-leaves, it ſmiles for the preſent, but will frown ſeverely afterward; 'tis an Iron Chain plaited over with Gold, beautiful in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, to attract and deceive the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but they will one day feel its weight and hardneſs, if they don't make an early diſcovery of the baſe ends he has who offers it, who will be their ruine at laſt, ſince they can't ſubſiſt, but by a due ballance between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> I conclude then, that 'tis the King of <hi>Englands</hi> apparent Intereſt, for ſelf-preſervation,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152962:33"/>and advancing of Trade, to oppoſe the King of <hi>France</hi> his Conqueſts in the <hi>Law Countries;</hi> for if he does not, and ſuppoſing that after the loſs of that Countrey, Fortune favours him, and lets him be Maſter of all the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen Provinces (which may very well come to paſs, if the <hi>States</hi> are not ſeconded, and ſtand only upon their own Leggs) in what a condition will <hi>England</hi> be? <hi>France</hi> will be ſtronger at Sea, and more Potent in the <hi>Indies</hi> than ſhe; <hi>France</hi> will interfere with her in Traffique every day, ſhe will conſtantly have a brave Navy at Sea, and eſpecially in the Spring, which will not let a mouſe ſtir out of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Ports without leave, and upon the leaſt reſentment, farewel <hi>England</hi> to all intents and purpoſes, ſince there's no body left who will or dare lift up a finger in her defence.</p>
               <p>Moreover <hi>Englands</hi> beſt Policy is to keep <hi>France</hi> under, not only to maintain her Dominion of the Seas, but alſo to find a convenient opportunity for the recovery of her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient <hi>Demeſnes</hi> which <hi>France</hi> keeps from her for Example, <hi>Britain, Normandy, Poitou, Languedock,</hi> and all <hi>France</hi> too, which belongs to it by the Marriage of the King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> with <hi>Margaret,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Philip the Fair,</hi> from this Match came <hi>Henry</hi> V. of <hi>England,</hi> who had as much Right to <hi>France</hi> as the Dauphin has to <hi>Spain:</hi> For the three Sons of <hi>Philip the Fair, Lovis Hutin, Philip the Long,</hi> and <hi>Charles the Fair</hi> dyed all without Iſſue-male, and it was after this, when the King of <hi>England</hi> ſued for his Right to the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> that the <hi>Salique</hi> Law was firſt intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc't, uſher'd in by a Sermon which the Biſhop of <hi>Beauvais</hi> preacht before the Convention of the <hi>States,</hi> proving by the Goſpel, which ſayes, <hi>The Lillies ſpin not,</hi> that by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence the <hi>Flower de lis</hi> which repreſents <hi>France,</hi> ought never to fall to the Diſtaff: But that Law could only af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect what was to come, and not what was paſt. Afterward
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152962:34"/>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> V. King of <hi>England</hi> came over into <hi>France</hi> with a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Army, won ſeveral Victories, and at laſt Married <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> VI. and in the year 1421 it was ſinally decreed and concluded, that <hi>Henry</hi> ſhould be King of <hi>France:</hi> Now <hi>Iſabel</hi> Queen of <hi>France,</hi> Mother to <hi>Catherine</hi> Queen of <hi>England,</hi> made her laſt Will in favour of her Son in Law, and declared him Heir to all her Eſtate, and to the Crown, which in my judgment is a great addition to the Right which the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have to the Realm of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the King of <hi>France</hi> had but had that Right to <hi>England</hi> which the King of <hi>England</hi> has to <hi>France,</hi> what a Company of Manifeſtoes and Writings ſhould we have flie about? to demonſtrate his <hi>juſt pretentions,</hi> as he calls every thing he is pleaſed to lay a claim to.</p>
               <p>So that let the King of <hi>England</hi> take a view of <hi>France</hi> which way ſoever he will, he ought alway to ſuſpect her, and ſtand upon his guard, as againſt one whom he certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knows to be his Enemy. He may juſtly be aſſured that he does not coaks him ſo without a deſign to get ſomething out of him, and becauſe he knows him the only one who is able to counterpoize his Affairs: Therefore 'tis no wonder that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. took ſo much pains to ſupply the late King <hi>Charles</hi> II. Neceſſities, and ſatisfie his Pleaſure, Mounſieur <hi>Barillen,</hi> and Madam <hi>Portſmouth</hi> can juſtifie what I ſay, but I can aſſure you that the King of <hi>France</hi> regards neither Princes nor private Perſons one jot farther than as they are for his turn: Nay farther, Even Vertue it ſelf is only eſteem'd by him, ſo long as ſhe ſquares with his Intereſt: What value pray did he put upon either Princes or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes during <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s Government? Were they not obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to retire (not to ſay driven) out of <hi>France?</hi> What ſubſiſtnance or help had their Princes in their Exile from
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152962:34"/>
                  <hi>France?</hi> No, 'tis to the Family of <hi>Orange,</hi> that they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, which furniſht them with conſiderable Sums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; but on the contrary <hi>France</hi> was the promoter of the late Troubles of <hi>England,</hi> ſhe gave the Princes no protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and never contributed the leaſt toward the re-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the late King in his Throne.</p>
               <p>All this conſidered, neither juſt reſentment from the Royal Family, nor the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt can decently allow of ſuch cloſe Alliances with <hi>France,</hi> as ſhall be able to make <hi>England</hi> ſhut her Eyes, or be a by-ſtander, whilſt <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. takes the <hi>Low Countries:</hi> But on the other ſide, ſhe ought to be continually in a poſture to hinder her in every the leaſt attempt ſhe makes towards it, and to make uſe of the Six Regiments in <hi>Holland,</hi> which the <hi>States</hi> won't refuſe upon ſuch an occaſion, to prevent the King of <hi>France</hi> his bringing more Men down upon <hi>Flanders:</hi> I am perſwaded that thoſe Six Regiments would be able to cope with double the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>French;</hi> and thus by <hi>Englands</hi> only ſhowing of her Teeth, <hi>Europe</hi> will be ſafe: <hi>Reſiſt the Devil, and he will flie from you:</hi> But if you are afraid of him, he'l ſoon maſter you. <hi>France</hi> has cut out work for King <hi>James</hi> now Reigning: The Enterprize which he has taken in hand is ſo great, that many Men fear, and others hope, that he will never get quit of it with his Life. 'Tis no time to change Laws when the Enemy is at the Gate: 'Tis not convenient at all times, to think of working great Converſions, ſome Battles muſt be fought, to let the World ſee a Character both of a Soldier and a Polititian. All the World expected this and more from the King. His Mighty Courage put all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> in hopes, that he would be an Univerſal Comforter to them, and would afford ſome reſpite to <hi>Spain.</hi> But alas! What can his Allies and <hi>Spain</hi> hope for, whilſt his ſole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is to pleaſe the Jeſuits, kindles a fire in his own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152962:35"/>which it may be he won't be able to quench when he pleaſes; and ſo long as he does ſo, he dares not call a Legal Free Parliament.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spain</hi> loſt her ſelf by baniſhing the <hi>Moors</hi> out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. <hi>France</hi> is weakned by the Converſions ſhe has wrought, and by driving out the Hugonots, and ſhe has a great mind that the King of <hi>England</hi> would follow her Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. We muſt not rob God of his Right, Converſions only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him, and he is able to convert the whole World with one Word: Therefore leaving the care of this to God, the King of <hi>England</hi> ought to mind the ſafety of his States, avoid being made the King of <hi>France</hi> his Cully, and make him keep at home, and not fall upon his Neighbours Lands, which ought to be the Barrier between them: Thus the King will do his Honour and Conduct but Juſtice, and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the expectation of all <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Politick Spirit of <hi>France,</hi> and its Maxims, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>United Provinces.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>States</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> after they had conſtrained <hi>Spain</hi> by force of Arms to acknowledge them for Free, High and Mighty <hi>States,</hi> depending on none but God alone; were for ſome time the admiration of their Neighbours, and every one laboured to procure their Friendſhip and Alliance, and it may be ſaid that they were looked upon as the Umpires of <hi>Europe;</hi> but ſince the War in 1672, this High Reputation hath been leſſened, and <hi>France</hi> hath been ſo cunning to play her Cards ſo well, that ſhe had well nigh reduc't them to nothing; if by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lookt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152962:35"/>for change, the People had not put the whole ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement and command into the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s hands, and if ſome perſons of ill deſigns had not been brought to condign puniſhment. But God whom it pleaſed by his Providence to protect and preſerve this little Country, did after the ſiege of <hi>Norden</hi> ſend ſuch a panick fear amongſt its Enemies, that they broke up their Camp with more ſpeed than they came, yet the thing which did moſt contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to theſe misfortunes, beſides the Treachery of <hi>France</hi> was their being unprovided of good Forces, and a good Head for the Army. Theſe Provinces relyed wholly upon the Peace, and treacherous deceitful promiſes of <hi>France,</hi> which all a long in time of Peace carryed on a deſign againſt the ſaid Provinces. We ſee that amidſt Peace, the Militia For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces grew ſlothful: Eaſe ſmiles for a little while, Men quite forſake the care of Arms, and give themſelves only to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing profitable and gainful: When the Enemy approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, Men flie oftentimes to their ſhame (far from that Glory which was heretofore the prevailing Paſſion) as we might have obſerved in the late Wars. <hi>France</hi> was ſure ſo long as the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> had no Captain-General, the Militia would be but ill provided, and no ways upon their Guard, and this is the reaſon why ſhe was ſo very careful to hinder the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> from being advanced to thoſe Dignities and Commands which he at preſent enjoys, by ſtrengthning and poyſoning the contrary Party: By this means the <hi>States</hi> grew weaker and weaker every day: Their Forces were diſperſt, their Fortifications neglected, and their ſtrongeſt places fell to decay; their Magazines but ill provided with Ammunition, whilſt <hi>France</hi> levyed Men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares, entered into ſecret Alliances with <hi>England,</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Cologne,</hi> and Biſhop of <hi>Munſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:152962:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Du Pleſſis</hi> ſaith very well, that every <hi>State</hi> is not thought ſtrong or weak, but in compariſon to the ſtrength and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Neighbours; that 'tis for that end that wiſe Princes alwayes keep a counterpoize as much as poſſible, that they may remain in peace and amity together, and ſo ſoon as ever that fails, peace and amity is diſſolved, not being grounded upon any thing but mutual fear, or reſpect for one another: Now this is ſo true, that every Prince is jealous of the leaſt Levy or Motion of his Neighbour, even amidſt Peace, or Ceſſation of Arms; and do perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually obſerve it, and labour to get a true Information of the deſigns of his Enemy or Neighbour even before they be hatched; for thereby his reſolutions are ſpoiled; now this is the thing wherein abundance of Princes and States (who ſtand upon coſt and charges) are to ſeek: This is a piece of Covetouſneſs that ſometimes coſts its Maſter and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple dear, and at laſt occaſioneth a War, which perhaps might have been prevented with a ſmall matter. <hi>France</hi> is ſo well aſſured of the Truth of it, that ſhe lets nothing ſlip upon ſuch occaſions: Her Embaſſadors in all the Courts of <hi>Europe</hi> have Money for that purpoſe; and they can do their Maſter no better ſervice, nor ſooner win his favour, than by corrupting one or more of that Princes Council at whoſe Court they reſide: It is their chief ſtudy Night and Day, and ſpare nothing to accompliſh it: When they come ſhort of the good Man, they are ſure to win the Wife, that ſhe may now and then ask her Husband; (nay, rather than fail, one of the Children may ſerve the turn) whether or no he was ſucceſsful in ſuch and ſuch a buſineſs: They apply themſelves in like manner to the Servants, whom they reward according to their ſervices. Theſe Maxims prove very lucky to them in <hi>States</hi> where there are many Heads, as in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> who are a great rub in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152962:36"/>the King of <hi>France</hi> his way in his Conqueſt of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> for he knows that having ſome of them, he may make ſure of the reſt, ſo that his main buſineſs is to lull the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> aſleep by a Truce which he breakes at pleaſure, ſuppoſing at that time they may neglect their Militia, as heretofore they did, and buſie themſelves only with Trading, for the King knows that the <hi>States</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Wits about them, and upon their Guard, they will never conſent to the taking of the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> at leaſt that they ought not to do it, ſince that there lyes the bounds between <hi>France</hi> and them, which they ought to have a care of, as of their Neighbours Houſe leaſt it be ſet on Fire. So that to bring about his Deſign what hath not the Count <hi>d'Avaux</hi> done to divide one Province againſt another, nay even the Cities of <hi>Holland,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What did he not promiſe, what did he not engage, to accompliſh his Deſigns? However they were not managed with ſuch ſecrecy, but that the very Boys in the ſtreets ſmoak't them out, through the frequent Journeys this Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador ſo often made to this great City, neither is <hi>Mom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi> to be thought the only Actor in this Affair, for when he retired to <hi>France,</hi> he left many Agents behind him, to further the deſign in the Night, not daring to appear in the Day: but the beſt was, Count <hi>d'Avaux</hi> became at length to be better underſtood, the People began to ſuſpect his Doctrine, for his abuſing the eaſineſs and good nature of many of them, made them ſenſible of his practice, and illude his Deſigns: but the Policies of <hi>France</hi> are more perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in fomenting the differences between <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> well knowing the uniting of both their Forces together might give <hi>France</hi> it's Mortal Wound. How ſweet therefore muſt their Diviſions be to <hi>France,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152962:37"/>when they ſpring from among themſelves? The laſt War between theſe two, aroſe from ſome differences in point of Traffick, and whilſt the King of <hi>England</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for the War, the King of <hi>France</hi> offered his Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance towards an accommodation with the <hi>States,</hi> on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe onely to delude them, as they well perceived after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards being amazed that when they drew near to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, <hi>France</hi> on the ſudden ſided with <hi>England,</hi> and at the ſame time the one gave the Aſſault by Sea, the other by Land: and ſo aſſuring to themſelves an intire Conqueſt of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> they divided their Spoils, the one taking the Maritime places, and <hi>France</hi> the other, but they miſ-underſtood one another about <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> each ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining to poſſeſs that himſelf; but there was no occaſion for their caſting Lots for it, for God ſuffer'd it not to fall into their hands: afterwards each drew home their Forces, according to the Peace which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were the firſt movers of. Then did <hi>France</hi> labour what it could to ſtrip the <hi>States</hi> of their Allies, it's King foreſeeing the Dice would turn, and that the <hi>Dutch</hi> might rally, their Soldiers being in great Diſcipline under an experienced General, then did the King give up <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> and did whatever elſe lay in his power to promote the peace at <hi>Nimeghen:</hi> Since which time he has alwayes bark'd at a diſtance, and did ſo much dread the <hi>States</hi> levying the laſt 16000 men, that Count <hi>d'Avaux</hi> uſed all Stratagems to prevent it, as he will do at all times whenever the <hi>States</hi> diſcover an inclination to arm; becauſe that would prove ſome hinderance to his encroaching deſigns, and here I muſt repeat again, how much it is the Intereſt of the <hi>States,</hi> to prevent their Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers from being ſwallowed up, which certainly in a ſhort time will become a prey to the Uſurper, upon a more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretence then that King has uſually made uſe of: He
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152962:37"/>may publickly declare upon what right his pretenſions are grounded, how that, without the leaſt diſpute theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces did formerly belong to <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> to <hi>Philip</hi> the Firſt, to <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, and after that to <hi>Philip</hi> the Second, and that theſe were in rightful poſſeſſion of them till they afterwards Rebelled, and by force extorted their Liberty: He will offer them, in caſe they will freely ſubmit themſelves to his Dominion, to maintain their Ancient Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and reſerve to them the free Exerciſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and alſo exempt them from all impoſitions as he does his <hi>French</hi> Subjects; which if they ſhall refuſe to do, then will he attack them with his Army, as he did in the year 1672. fearing no oppoſition from any of the <hi>Catholick Princes,</hi> before whoſe eyes he hath all along caſt a miſt with the ſpecious pretences of Religion; but if the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> continue ſtill to be lull'd aſleep, ſhe with all her Catholiciſm will be irrecoverably undone.</p>
               <p>But I perceive the <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> next to God, muſt depend wholly upon their own ſtrength, and need onely be afraid of <hi>France,</hi> and to level their whole Forces againſt her, whoſe deſign for theſe many years has been to ſuppreſs them, and if not wholly to deſtroy them, yet at leaſt to reduce them ſo low, as they ſhould wholly depend upon her.</p>
               <p>The King would willingly agree with them after the ſame manner as we read in the Fable the Wolf would have done with the Sheep, diſmiſs your Shepherd and your Dog, cries the Wolf to theſe poor ſimple Creatures, and then will we enter into a ſtrict Friendſhip and Alliance together, and live peaceably one with another; thus ſays Mr. King, Caſhier your General, disband your Veterane Soldiers, 'twill be good Husbandry now in this time of peace, and you may aſſure your ſelves of my Friendſhip, and take your
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152962:38"/>eaſe during this Ceſſation, and ſo we will live Friendly and quietly together; but the <hi>Italian</hi> tells us, <hi>Truſt not, and you will never be deceived:</hi> Thus as I laid down before, 'tis beſt for them to rely wholly upon their own proper ſtrength, and be ever provided with a ſubſtantial Navy, both for Cruiſing up and down and for Convoy's, and alſo to have another ready to put to Sea, their ſtrength at Sea is the right-hand of the <hi>States,</hi> and which will eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe the ſtorms which <hi>France</hi> do often threaten her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours with: and if the <hi>States</hi> would ever be perſwaded to train up a ſufficient number of Seamen, to be in conſtant readineſs to Man their Frigats whenever neceſſity required, it would produce this double advantage; 1. The State would be ever furniſhed with men ready for her Defence, without the Trouble of ſeeking where to levy them, and theſe will be skilful enough by the continual ſervice. 2. She would draw from neighbouring Havens many Mariners that would proffer their ſervices, but eſpecially ſuch of the <hi>States</hi> ſubjects as were in Foreign ſervice would chooſe rather to return home when they ſhould be ſure to be in ſervice upon the Land or the Water, the whole year round; thoſe who are abroad, need not be frighted to return home by ſharp Proclamations: 'Tis certain <hi>France</hi> can't brag much upon this account, for I am ſure moſt of the ſhips ſhe ſends out but eſpecially the Pilots are all <hi>Dutch,</hi> ſhe confiding more in the skil and experience of them than of her own men, who never dare venture upon long Voyages; and if ever the <hi>States,</hi> ſhould reſolve upon ſo beneficial a method, the Policies of <hi>France</hi> would immediately be perceived to rouſe, and Count <hi>d'Avaux,</hi> hound-like would hunt from Town to Town to oppoſe it: but he begins now to grow very angry, becauſe of the ſmall effect which his large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes have hitherto produced, and meerly for want of their being duly tempered with Truth and Honeſty, the main
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152962:38"/>ſupporters of the Credit and Reputation of a Miniſter of State in a Foreign Country, but the King is obliged to this great Man for putting ſeveral ſtories of their High and Mightineſſes into his Head, that they have no cauſe to thank him for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>France</hi> notwithſtanding is mightily aſſiſted in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> by the Jeſuits and other Foreign Prieſts, who are hired to ſift out, and divert the good intentions of the People, they are crept into the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Court, where they find private Friends to ſerve them on all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; they have the impudence to brag of their Intelligence of things done in his private Chamber, and they omit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that tends to the well acting of their parts; they ſwarm in his Troops and Garriſons, whence they tranſmit their intelligence to the <hi>Hague</hi> the common Office of adreſs, and as it were the Receptacle of the other Cities and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces; the greater caution therefore ought to be uſed, for all theſe Vermine are warmed by <hi>France,</hi> who is ever in action, and will deny nothing to any one whom ſhe thinks can be ſerviceable to her: I my ſelf remember, that not long ago, a Foot-man of one of the <hi>States</hi> Deputies was offered Four Ducatoons a week, to betray whatever his Maſter ſhould ſpeak of, either at his own Table, or in Diſcourſe with the other Deputies, but the Valet with reaſon and height of indignation refuſed the baſeneſs.</p>
               <p>Thus we may obſerve the <hi>French</hi> Policy, make uſe of all wayes, how much therefore ought they to be upon their Guard, to keep off her blows: I my ſelf obſerve the chief Cities about the <hi>Hague</hi> infeſted with Spies, who hunt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Table, and dayly change their Dining-places, except they find ſome good bit or other to divert them, how cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious then ought they to be, who are obliged to frequent Ordinaries: Others of theſe little Fellows ſcrew themſelves
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152962:39"/>into all Companies, others of them into the Court, at ſuch times when the Prince and Princeſs Dine and Sup publickly, and all this only to obſerve what is ſaid, and to make report of every ſmall accident, even of the very Fire and Fewel: Whenever theſe little News-Carriers happen upon any thing of moment, away they ſcoure like the Baſques to the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadors, where they are ſure of a Dinner, his Table being generally filled up with theſe kind of Cattle: I could name a dozen of theſe Animals, who to my knowledge are thus maintained, beſides others who manage theſe concerns with more privacy, acting only in the dark: The Count <hi>de Caravas,</hi> was one of the chief of them; a Man very much eſteemed of, though in my mind only like a chip in pottage, not being ſo cautious as he ſhould have been, for he went about at Noon-day, and through the great Gates to carry his news: Two others whom I know to be Jeſuits, are dayly diſguiſed in Officers Habits at the Princes <hi>Levie,</hi> his times of Dining and Supping, haunting the Court all the day long, where they are ingaged in ſo many Intrigues, and have ſuch numbers of Acquaintance, that they well underſtand what advice to give to their Friends the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, for after all they are <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries, and wholly devoted to that Service; others of this ſort get to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the Kitchin, where theſe Cattle are too too dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous: The concluſion therefore is Natural, to keep a watch on all ſides, in all times, in Peace, in War, upon the Motions of <hi>France,</hi> whoſe Maxims are deſtructive and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, whoſe King is both perjured and a Lyar, who, under the colour of eſtabliſhing univerſally the Catholick Religion (which he himſelf in his Life and Faith renounces) has no other end than the Extent of his own Dominion over all <hi>Europe;</hi> firſt over the Proteſtant Princes if he can, and then over the Catholick; and thus not only to be declared
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:152962:39"/>
                  <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour, but alſo Univerſal Emperour of <hi>Europe,</hi> and 'tis lamentable to behold with what a Covetous Eye from <hi>Verſailes</hi> he looks upon the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces:</hi> 'Tis therefore adviſable for the <hi>States</hi> and People of theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, to put in practice what our Saviour once adviſed the <hi>Jews, Watch, for ye know not the hour in which the Thief will come:</hi> So, ſay I, be ever in a readineſs to oppoſe him, whenever he ſhall endeavour to poſſeſs himſelf of their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and uſurp upon the Territories of his Neighbours, and by degrees upon that which God Almighty has diſpoſed of to the wiſe Government of the <hi>States,</hi> for <hi>France</hi> muſt be look't upon in theſe dayes as the common Enemy to all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicks, as the Scourge of all that deny his Power: True it is, that his fear of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> by much exceeds his love for them, 'tis very convenient to keep him in this fear, by repelling him whenever he advances beyond his own Territories, and not ſo much to truſt to Count <hi>D' Avaux</hi>'s deceitful Remonſtrances, and his being againſt their putting themſelves into a poſture of defence, ought aſſuredly to perſwade them that it is alſo contrary to his Maſters deſire, otherwiſe why ſhould he trouble himſelf to oppoſe it. The <hi>States</hi> are more particularly engaged to be upon their Guard, and to neglect nothing which may tend to their defence, becauſe of their too near Neighbour the Cardinal of <hi>Furſtemburg,</hi> who is lately Elected Co-adjutor of <hi>Cologne,</hi> a dangerous and active Man, and already poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with the Demon of <hi>France,</hi> whom the King can raiſe with his Money when he pleaſes, to the more eaſie redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Frontiers of the Provinces, and upon all occaſions will buoy up <hi>France</hi> in quarrelling with <hi>Holland</hi> upon the firſt notice given. The Spirit of <hi>France</hi> appears in all his Actions, ſo that he is equally as dangerous a Neighbour as the King himſelf, for his high Obligations to his Maſter will
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152962:40"/>oblige him alſo to concur in his deſigns of becoming the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarch, by ſwallowing up his Neighbours round about him, as will be ſeen in time, if ſome Courſe be'nt taken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Policies and Maxims of <hi>France,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Northern</hi> Princes.</head>
               <p>I Place the Kings of <hi>Swedeland</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> among the chief of the <hi>Northern</hi> Princes: Theſe are two Powerful Kingdoms, and although they are Neighbours, and nearly allyed by Marriages, yet notwithſtanding are ſo far from loving, that like <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> they mortally hate one another; and although their Intereſt, Trade, and narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Revenue ought to perſwade them to live amicably together, yet notwithſtanding all, their antipathy will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail; 'tis of high importance to <hi>France</hi> to have ever one of theſe Kings at his beck, that ſo ſhe may give a diverſion to the other, whenever the one ſhould have a mind to aſſiſt the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> or the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi> againſt her En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments. The <hi>Swede</hi> being the ſtronger, ſuits beſt with this deſign of <hi>France,</hi> between whom therefore there hath been a ſtrict Alliance, but the <hi>Swede</hi> being diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his Penſion, and treacherouſly dealt with in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Dutchy of <hi>Deux-Ponts,</hi> which deſcended to him after the Death of that Duke, but was miſerably impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſht by <hi>France</hi> in the Life of the Duke: Theſe things the <hi>Swede</hi> cannot put up, but for the preſent 'tis not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152962:40"/>to diſcover his reſentments, but reſerve them for a fairer opportunity, neither will <hi>France</hi> do any good now if ſhe ſhould preſent her <hi>Louis' d'or's</hi> put up like a barrel of Olives, as ſhe did formerly to his Ambaſſador to ſoften him at the Treaty of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> which ſhe her ſelf hath ſince bragged of: All this will be to ſmall purpoſe, for the <hi>Swede</hi> has already taſted ſufficiently of the bitter Spirit of <hi>France,</hi> and has reſolved to have nothing more to do with her. Therefore <hi>France</hi> goes now to the K. of <hi>Denmark,</hi> who had a mind next to ſee what kind of things theſe <hi>Louis' d'or's</hi> be, and therefore never ſtuck to ſide with her; when im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately Count <hi>de Roy</hi> was diſpatch't in quality of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſſimo, with ſeveral other <hi>French</hi> Officers, at whoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival the <hi>French</hi> Tricks forthwith diſcover'd themſelves, for Count <hi>de Roy</hi> immediately demanded on behalf of the King his Maſter, part of the ſupplies ſent from <hi>France,</hi> pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they were ſquander'd away to no purpoſe. The like Complement was formerly done to the Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh,</hi> but Kings and Princes muſt conſult the Honour of their Poſterity and the Ages to come, as well as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. What a Cypher in Hiſtory will a Mercenary Prince and an Hireling of <hi>France</hi> appear in future Ages, who is led like a Bear by the Noſe, and thus gives a Tarniſh to all his other Actions, which otherwiſe might be worthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration; he muſt not imagine ſuch baſeneſs will dye with his Perſon, there are ever found ſome that will be Friends to truth, all Pens are not ſo Mercenary as <hi>Varilla</hi>'s and <hi>Pelliſſon</hi>'s.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as <hi>France</hi> has made as much uſe of the <hi>Dane</hi> as ſhe can, and finds any other to be of more advantage to her, ſhe will forſake him as one too much for his own ends, pretending ſome ſham-quarrel or other, (as the <hi>Turks</hi> do) to fall out with him about his Penſion, as ſhe formerly
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152962:41"/>ſerved the <hi>Swede:</hi> and if the Houſe of <hi>Lunenburgh</hi> would have ſwallowed the Bait, the <hi>Dane</hi> ſhould not have warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf by <hi>France</hi> ſo long as he has already done.</p>
               <p>But beſides the Ignominy which will follow a Sovereign, who inſtead of depending ſolely upon the King of Kings, Bluſhes not in becoming a Vaſſal to his Equal, and giving occaſion to <hi>France</hi> to boaſt like the Centurion in the Goſpel, <hi>I bid my ſervant do this, and he doth it, and to another, go, and he goeth, and to another, come, and he cometh.</hi> I ſay, beſides this Baſeneſs, its moſt pernicious Policy, (though I doubt the <hi>Dane</hi>'s too heavy to diſcern it) for a ſmall dirty ſum of Money, and which ſerves onely to maintain his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Troops, to render himſelf an Enemy to all <hi>Europe,</hi> and in particular to his potent Neighbours, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the aſſiſtance of whom both <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Norway</hi> muſt fall to the ground. For I do maintain, that it lyes in the power of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> by a Remonſtrance to do more Miſchief to thoſe two Kingdoms in one year, than they can ever recover in ten by all their Subſidies and Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from <hi>France:</hi> I confeſs, by the ſhelter from <hi>France,</hi> he eaſily became Maſter of <hi>Holſtein;</hi> but alas, good man, can he imagine to keep it, for ſurely that Country will take ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to oblige him to quit it, as ſoon as ever his Maſter the K. of <hi>France</hi> ſhall be routed out of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Were there but once a Peace concluded between the two Emperors, the victorious Chriſtian Army would certainly make the Uſurper diſgorge, and reduce his Stomach to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: Soft and fair goes far. Had it not been for the Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Dane</hi> had never made that Aſſault upon <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> which became the Grave to ſo many brave <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>French</hi> that ſerved in that Attempt; the unlucky Fort of the <hi>Starr</hi> ſtopt them in their Career, from whence with the loſs of Two Thouſand men, they were
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152962:41"/>obliged to retreat with ſhame and confuſion thereby becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the laughing-ſtock to all <hi>Europe</hi> beſides.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Denmark</hi> as well as many others, is not real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of his own Intereſt, but ſuffers himſelf to be dazl'd by this Golden Sun, which <hi>France</hi> immediately diſplayes to ſuch as ſhe has a mind to corrupt; ſhe ever has in reſerve her <hi>Nimigen</hi> Olives to gratifie ſuch, whoſe aſſiſtance ſhe ſhall ſtand in need of: But 'tis a thing much to be hoped for, that his Majeſtie of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Eyes may be opened, as well as the <hi>Swedes;</hi> and that he would retrieve himſelf from theſe Shackles, and have recourſe to his other Allies, in whoſe power it is to make the Trade of his Kingdoms to flouriſh, and his Revenues to increaſe, without being obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to keep up ſuch a number of uſeleſs Troops as he does at preſent: But <hi>France</hi> well knows the neceſſity of having at her beck one of thoſe <hi>Northern Princes,</hi> for fear they ſhould unite in a ſtrict Alliance, and ſo league with her Enemies: This Policy of <hi>France</hi> is the <hi>Apple of diſcord,</hi> and ſhe not being able to be without a <hi>Northern</hi> Allie, if <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> had ſtood off a while, <hi>France</hi> muſt have purchaſed her Friendſhip at a double rate: The Marriage which <hi>France</hi> propoſed for P— <hi>G</hi>— with the P—s <hi>A</hi>— was only to ſtrengthen <hi>her</hi> Party, and to make <hi>her</hi> Alliance the ſurer, this made her willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray the Charges thereof; P— <hi>G</hi>— <hi>himſelf, nor the King his Brother having not much Money to ſpare for that purpoſe,</hi> this coſt <hi>France</hi> a Hundred Thouſand Crowns to ſecure to her ſide, as ſhe thought, a <hi>Creature</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> who ſhould on all occaſions further her deſigns; and to knit this the ſtronger, <hi>he</hi> would have <hi>had him</hi> believe, <hi>he</hi> ſhould ſucceed to the Crown after the Death of King <hi>James</hi> II. to the apparent prejudice of the next undoubted Heireſs, To make which the more feaſible, he would have fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152962:42"/>Jealouſies between the two Siſters and their Husbands, well foreſeeing a terrible blow if Affairs ſhould change, and the Succeſſion be kept in the right Line. 'Tis true, the King of <hi>France</hi> might think to engage P— <hi>G</hi>— in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Scurvy buſineſs, by contriving a Civil War in <hi>England,</hi> after the Deceaſe of the King now Reigning; but I cannot deviſe after he ſhould have involved him in this Labyrinth, how he will extricate him: <hi>The Duke of</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth <hi>(for all he was the Son of a King) is a caution to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Subject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis well known the <hi>French</hi> King is very earneſt with the King of <hi>England</hi> by his Jeſuites, to demand of the Firſt Parliament he can get at his beck and Devotion, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to choſe a Succeſſor after the Example of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. <hi>and once gaining that, to advance the P—s</hi> A— <hi>to the Crown before any other;</hi> but many weary ſtep, and a far Compaſs muſt be taken before he get ſo far: Firſt of all, The King of <hi>England</hi> muſt have a Parliament at his Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Secondly, This Parliament muſt grant his Requeſt: Thirdly, The King muſt chooſe (nay who can tell but Death may prevent all theſe:) In the Fourth place, 'Tis meet the People conſent to this Choice: Nay laſt of all, 'Tis abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely convenient that the P—<hi>s</hi> of <hi>O</hi>— as Lawful Heireſs acquieſce in ſuch determinations.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> King who is no admirer of Vertue, but as it keeps pace with his Intereſts, underſtanding thoſe Noble Qualities, and Great Vertues the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed withal, that ſhe will no ſooner ſhine upon the Throne of her Anceſtors, but ſhe will attract and win the Hearts of all her Subjects, both by her Wiſdom, and alſo ſtrict Alliance with her Neighbours: He ſees that theſe Ties and Bonds may in time make him diſgorge what he hath ſwallowed, and repent of all the ſorrows he hath cauſed, and ſtill doth cauſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152962:42"/>Chriſtendom to ſuffer: Who knows but God may have marked out this Great and Vertuous Princeſs as a ſecond <hi>Judith</hi> to put this Blaſphemous <hi>Holofernes</hi> to Death: Yea, this is what this Uſurper and Diſturber of Chriſtendom is ſo ſenſibly apprehenſive of, and endeavours to hinder, by feeing and corrupting the Great Men of <hi>England,</hi> by making ſure of all the Catholicks, and of <hi>Ireland</hi> it ſelf, thereby to give them relief in caſe of neceſſity.</p>
               <p>But P— <hi>G</hi>—and his Conſort P—s <hi>A</hi>— will look bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter about them, and will not ſuffer themſelves to be deluded by this deceitful Spirit of <hi>France:</hi> They ſee all its pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and deceitful Maxims, and will wait for the time Providence hath determined for their Succeſſion to the Crown; they have already gained the Peoples Hearts, the Eſteem and Reputation of <hi>Europe;</hi> and of their Allies; and by this means may be aſſured to back and juſtifie their rightful Titles at that time, in caſe any one ſhould dare to oppoſe it.</p>
               <p>As for the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Lunenburg,</hi> they are taken notice of and watched, they are encompaſt with <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries on all ſides, who do nothing but continually ſet before them the Advantages that may accrew to them by accepting of the <hi>French</hi> Kings Penſions; or to ſpeak the truth, make themſelves Slaves to <hi>Lewis le Grand,</hi> juſt following the King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Example, to dance after his pipe. The <hi>French</hi> pence often ſtick too cloſe to the fingers of the Miniſters of thoſe Courts, <hi>Bois-David</hi> and his Kinſman St. <hi>Pouage</hi> could tell us fine ſtories of their tricks, and certain too, they could deliver brave Memorials concerning that Court, had not <hi>Bois-David</hi> been for the Kings turn, he durſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have had the face to have come home into <hi>France</hi> as he did, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing found guilty upon the ſcore of a Duel with <hi>Aubjou;</hi> for there is no fault how hainous ſoever, but the King pardons, if the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor be judged needful for his Intereſt and Ambition: We are confident the King proffers vaſt Sums to withdraw the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Lunenburg</hi> from their true Intereſt, and ſo bring them under the <hi>French</hi> Yoak; but I would have them diſabus'd: 'Tis no wayes Honourable nor creditable for Free and Soveraign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to ſtoop ſo low as to be <hi>Mercenary</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> and 'tis certain all theſe offers are for nothing elſe but to looſen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their honeſt true Allies, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Swedes,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and the States of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152962:43"/>pecial Intereſt it is to hold faſt, and be firmly united, as well by reaſon of the nearneſs of their <hi>States,</hi> as upon the account of Trading; and that fair correſpondence which hath alwayes reigned amongſt them: So that a Man may ſafely avouch they ſerve to maintain, and mutually preſerve one another. Now <hi>France</hi> hath a deſign in it, in meaning to oblige the Princes of <hi>Lunenbourg</hi> to come over to her Intereſt; for ſhould the King of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Spain</hi> chance to dye ſuddenly, ſhe would have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for thoſe three forementioned Powers to be able to oppoſe them with the <hi>French</hi> Troops joyned to theirs, in caſe any one of them ſhould be in action.</p>
               <p>'Tis moſt evident, that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. ought to labour as he doth to procure himſelf Allies to ſecond his Deſigns upon the ſame ſcore as he doth for <hi>Denmark,</hi> whether it be to hinder the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> paſſage into <hi>England,</hi> or when he means to fall upon <hi>Holland</hi> in good earneſt; theſe two concerns go to his heart, and is his ſole grief conſidering the Grand Conqueſt of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, who will be like to grieve him to the heart with his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious Army after peace made; nay, and perhaps make him loſe his longing, to put ſome of his great deſigns in Execution, for which he labours tooth and nail, and now begins to cool up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, to the end he may ſo well order his buſineſs, that he may neither meet with any impediment, or at leaſt that he may divert and buſie thoſe who mean to withſtand it.</p>
               <p>I dare ſafely affirm, that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is the only Man the <hi>French</hi> King dreads, and that the very thoughts of the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of a Royal Princeſs to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Crown puts him in a deadly fright, which gives him a Stool without a Pill, knowing withal that this as great a Politician as Captain (not knowing what Corruption means) perfectly verſt in the true intereſt of <hi>Europe,</hi> will ſay as Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did, that none had any thing to do to pretend to the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> and will not endure that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King of <hi>France</hi> nor any other ſhould make himſelf Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of it, which will be very feaſable when he ſhall be advanced to this Dignity, and this is the reaſon why the Spirit of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great encompaſſeth the Earth, and would fain aſſociate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with as many Princes as poſſibly he can to ſhelter himſelf from the impending Storm and Tempeſt, and ſecure him from that Thunder that is ready to break out againſt him.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:152962:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poland</hi> is at a great diſtance from <hi>France,</hi> can neither hurt it by Sea or Land, but can do him great ſervice indirectly, as croſſing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Emperour, or by falling upon <hi>Swedeland,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Swedeland</hi> when <hi>France</hi> thinks good; for there wants not a plauſible excuſe when a Prince means to make an attempt. <hi>Caſimir</hi> Son of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmond</hi> had a lawful one indeed; for this <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> being as yet King of <hi>Sweeden,</hi> was elected King of <hi>Poland:</hi> He kept nevertheleſs his firſt Kingdom, until Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his Uncle was proclaimed King in the abſence of his Nephew King <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> who ſent a Senate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Forty Jeſuits to have full power of deciding all State-Matters, and were to reſide at <hi>Stockholm,</hi> being diſpatched with full inſtructions by Patent, impowering them with Royal Authority: But when the Senate was arrived in <hi>Stockholm</hi> Road, Prince <hi>Charles</hi> with all the Nobility went out to meet them with Twenty or Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ships to do the more Honour to theſe new Senate. This Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron coming round about the Veſſel of their Reverend Senators, gave them a broad-ſide, ſeeming to welcom them: Their Ships im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſprung divers leaks, and the Jeſuits went down to hold their firſt Seſſion in Quality of Senators at the bottom of the Salt Sea, none uſing any means to ſave one of them. In the upſhot, Prince <hi>Charles</hi> was Elected King, the Arch-biſhop diſpenſed with the Subjects Oath of Allegiance, which they took to <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> and his Uncle was proclaimed King.</p>
               <p>The <hi>French</hi> King thinks himſelf concern'd in the Election of a King of <hi>Poland;</hi> thither he uſually ſends an Embaſſador with ſome <hi>Lewiſſes</hi> to carry on the Election in favour of ſome Prince of his Faction, but eſpecially that he may not be true and ſtedfaſt to the Faction of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> King <hi>John</hi> now Reigning, his Queen being a <hi>French</hi> Lady, hath contributed very much to the Biſhop of <hi>Beauvais</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſador, to ſolicite in her behalf, becauſe the Moſt Chriſtian King always thought that by the Queens Interceſſion he ſhould prevail with the King to come over to his Intereſts, and he was not altogether miſtaken. True indeed the repulſe ſhe ſuffered from the King of beſtowing the Titles of Duke and Peer upon the Marquiſs <hi>D' Arquier</hi> her Father, and acknowledging her to be his Daughter, and of giving her the honour of Queen in caſe ſhe ſhould come into <hi>France,</hi> had a little cooled her; but when it will coſt the King but a little ſheet of Parchment to pleaſe a Prince, the King is extraordinary liberal of it at Court, eſpecially
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152962:44"/>if he have need of him. So likewiſe out of acknowledgment of theſe favours you ſee the King of <hi>Poland</hi> doth whatſoever his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour will have him; and St. <hi>Lewis</hi> is in great power in that Realm. Yet I don't look upon it as the true intereſt of <hi>Poland</hi> to make ſuch a ſtop, the wayes being ſo good ſince the deliverance and relief of <hi>Vienna,</hi> the iſſue and reſult of his great exploits would have Eternized his memory by giving a peace to the Grand Seignior upon advantageous terms for <hi>Poland;</hi> but the beſt of all was, he might have ſecured the Crown upon his Sons head, for queſtionleſs they could not in Juſtice have denyed it him, as an acknowledgment of all his Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. We are not ignorant that the Spirit of <hi>France,</hi> very prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal of promiſes, and fertile in cunningneſs, do aſcertain the King and Queen, that Prince <hi>Alexander</hi> their Son ſhall not fail of a Crown, and your Golden <hi>Lewiſſes</hi> work wonders: But who pray will give <hi>Lewis</hi> a leaſe of his Life till then? I muſt needs ſay he cauſed to be put under his Statue, <hi>Viro immortali,</hi> but I have found alſo in the ſame place, <hi>Cum fiſtula in ano.</hi> So that he may dye before the King of <hi>Poland;</hi> and if he do dye, it may ſo come to paſs that his Succeſſour may have ſo many Irons in the fire at home, that he will never think of ſeeking any more abroad.</p>
               <p>But now <hi>France</hi> offers the young Prince Royal of <hi>Poland</hi> for pledge of their Truth and Friendſhip the Princeſs <hi>de Conti la Valliere,</hi> whom they alſo offered to the Prince of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> as if there were no more Legitimate Princeſſes in <hi>Europe:</hi> I am perſwaded the King of <hi>France</hi> thinks he doth the <hi>Polonians</hi> a great deal of Honour, by offering them one of his Natural Daughters for to be their Queen. This would be fine to employ the Pens of thoſe Droll-Wits, <hi>Paſquin</hi> and <hi>Murforio:</hi> 'Tis certain, if the King of <hi>Poland</hi> ſhould give way to this aukward Contract of Alliance, it would be as much as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare plainly, that he no longer pretended to have the Crown of <hi>Poland</hi> for his Son, and that this Marriage was an act wholly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming it: I would have him rather follow the King of <hi>Portugals</hi> example; he was cunning enough to get himſelf diſentangled from the importunities of <hi>France,</hi> to ſtrengthen himſelf by his alliance with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and the Emperour, by his Marriage with the Princeſs Palatine of <hi>Newbourgh;</hi> he knew too well, that if ever <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. got footing in <hi>Spain,</hi> that his Kingdom would depend on his diſpoſal. One of the two Teeth this ſame <hi>Lewis</hi> was born with, is called Uſurping, the other Cruel; from the one proceeds
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152962:44"/>dependance, decorum, or convenience of Scituation, from the other, Treachery and Perſecution; you need not queſtion, if the King of <hi>France</hi> ſhould become King of <hi>Spain,</hi> but <hi>Portugal</hi> would be firſt of all inveſted, becauſe the <hi>Spaniard</hi> poſſeſt that Kingdom from <hi>Philip</hi> II. until <hi>Philip</hi> IV. time, which was about the year 1640, when the <hi>Portugueze</hi> ſhook off the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> yoak; Threeſcore years of poſſeſſion may plead preſcription, whereon to ground his right of dependance (there needs only thirty for a private man), beſides the right of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum, or commodious Scituation; for <hi>Portugal</hi> joyns upon the Kingdom of <hi>Caſtile, Aragon</hi> and <hi>Granada;</hi> he had not ſo good a Title to the Kingdom of <hi>Auſtraſie;</hi> nay he hath quite turned out the Princes who poſſeſſed one part of the Lands of that Kingdom for near 600 years. Fear keeps the Vineyard, as the <hi>French</hi> ſay, and diſtruſt is the mother of ſafety. If I had to do with Salvages, or with the King of <hi>Bantam</hi> or <hi>China,</hi> not knowing occurrences in our parts, it would be requiſite to enter upon an Hiſtorical Relation of all the ſlippery tricks <hi>France</hi> hath played this laſt Age, of all the Deceits, Cheats, Uſurpations, Injuſtices and Cruelties this preſent King hath put in practice to be Maſter of the Eſtates and the Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions of his Neighbours: But I ſpeak to <hi>Europeans,</hi> and they Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians too, who have ſeen with their Eyes, heard with their Ears, and have dayly before them, Princes diſpoyled and ſtript of their Poſſeſſions, ſo many People ruined, ſo many Cities taken, ſo many Houſes, now nothing but ruins and rubbiſh, Thouſands of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans reduced to Beggery; nay, and the Blood of his own Subjects ſtill a guſhing out in mighty ſtreams all over the Country; Theſe I ſay are ſpeaking Books, where all up and down you may find in huge Characters, <hi>Lewis the Great, Sacrifices all to his Ambition and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</hi> Now although all the World knows it, and though ſcarce a Prince but hath been couzen'd by him, yet he is ſo skilful to huſh them aſleep by the mild gentle raine of <hi>Lewiſſes,</hi> that ſome part of them cry, Lord what wouldſt thou have us do, and run headlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly, and with a kind of delight, to the ruin and deſtruction of their Iſſue. O how much need hath <hi>Europe</hi> of a good Oculiſt, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the Scales from the Eyes of a great many Princes, and once in their lives to open them for them, to the end, that every one know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what's good for himſelf, may lay aſide, and forſake the intereſt of <hi>France;</hi> they ought all unanimouſly to endeavour with might and main to procure him a Competitour to balance him, and retain and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152962:45"/>bind him up within his juſt bounds, and ſo diſable him, that he may no more trouble the earth by his ambition. One blow is ſufficient to do it; what need I tell you, all <hi>Europe</hi> ſees it: This will come to paſs when it ſhall pleaſe the Divine Wiſdom of the true Univerſal Monarch, King of Kings, to make it evident. We cannot but wiſh <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. long life, that he may be witneſs of all theſe things, and may have another <hi>Joſhua</hi> to ſtop the courſe of his Sun, for which the people of the earth ſo much long and put up their continual Prayers for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Spirit or Policy of <hi>France,</hi> and its Maximes, in regard of the <hi>Suiſſe Cantons</hi> his Allies, and of <hi>Savoy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Cantons</hi> of <hi>Switzerland</hi> being free and abſolute are govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by themſelves, hold of none but of God and their own valour; they are partly reformed, and partly Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; 'tis by reaſon of this difference of Religion, that they have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten variance amongſt themſelves, and give the King of <hi>France</hi> occaſion to lay hold on the opportunity, who makes good uſe of the eaſineſs of the latter to ſow the ſeed of diſſention among them. In time paſt they did no way border upon <hi>France,</hi> which was a great hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyneſs for the <hi>Cantons,</hi> but ſince the peace <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. made with the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the Country of <hi>Gex</hi> belonged to that Prince; then after that <hi>France</hi> which alwayes gets ground, did make encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>Alſatia, Franche Conte,</hi> and towards <hi>Burgundy,</hi> is at this time Neighbour to the <hi>Swiſſe</hi> on three ſeveral ſides: But <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. not content with that, had a mind to be a nearer Neighbour to his fellows, by the Fort of <hi>Huninghen</hi> within Canon ſhot; as we all know, from <hi>Baſil,</hi> the Governour hath lately attempted it, the <hi>Suiſſe</hi> were too much overſeen in being a little to well acquainted witſi the King of <hi>France,</hi> who thereby hath found out where their ſtrength and weakneſs lyes, and which way ſoever their affairs turn, whenſoever they are forced to quarrel with theſe Princes, it will alwayes fare with them as the Fable tells us, it did with the Earthen pot and Iron pot. Secondly, To lend ſo many Regiments to <hi>France,</hi> are as ſo many men loſt out of the <hi>Cantons,</hi> who, it may be, one day, may like young Vipers, deſtroy their common Mother,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152962:45"/>their Countrey; there are few <hi>Swiſſe</hi> Officers in the <hi>French</hi> Kings Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but let themſelves be corrupted by Marriages, then ſuffer their Eyes to be dazled by good places, and your <hi>Louis do'r,</hi> and ſo at once renounce both their Religion and Party, ſacrifice as <hi>Stoupa</hi> the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General would have done twice ſixteen <hi>Cantons</hi> to the Intereſt of <hi>France:</hi> He is not alone in his own gang, he hath, God knows, too many Diſciples; you'l find but very few who imitate the Sieur <hi>Daſſelouer</hi> of <hi>Berne</hi> heretofore Captain in the King's Service, who choſed rather to give over his employ, and break his Pike then do any thing contrary to the Treaty which his Superiours had entered to, about the paſſage of the <hi>Rhine</hi> againſt the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> they have alſo committed a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table fault in tying up their own hands, that they cannot ſend to <hi>Spain</hi> the like number of Soldiers, as they do to <hi>France:</hi> This reſtriction hath more of the <hi>Frenchman</hi> in it than the <hi>Cantons</hi> are aware of: They cannot but grant that they have ſuffered themſelves to be curb'd by the Fort at <hi>Huninghen,</hi> which but too much diſcovers the Kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; every <hi>chink</hi> in it are like ſo many open Mouths, crying out upon them, Awake, awake ye ſluggiſh People, and behold me, as the Emblem of the Uſurper, as a Monument rear'd in remembrance of your Liberty loſt.</p>
               <p>Now if this be not ſufficient to make the <hi>Cantons</hi> ſeriouſly reflect upon <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. his proceedings in reſpect of them, at leaſt that Cannon which the Fort of <hi>Huningen</hi> diſcharged upon the City of <hi>Baſil</hi> might open their Eyes, for the Uſurper gets ground every day, and I'le warrant you no ſooner ſhall he find a favourable oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, but he will improve his quarrel with <hi>Germany</hi> againſt them. Princes never want pretences: He will begin in good earneſt, to Will and Command, that the Biſhop and others of <hi>Baſil</hi> be reſtored, and that their Arrears be payd them from the time that they have been forced to forſake the Town; and if he be to enter by Force of Arms, and if he have obtained the leaſt Advantage, as the <hi>Cantons</hi> are tame enough to obtain Peace he would demand every year a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal as a mark of Homage for Tribute (as he did of the <hi>Hollanders</hi>) together with a great many Forces which the <hi>Swiſſe</hi> would be glad to ſupply him with upon his firſt Demand, and would place Biſhops as ſo many Emiſſaries in every City.</p>
               <p>I told you the <hi>French</hi> King takes advantage by the difference of Religion in the <hi>Cantons</hi> to foment diſcord amongſt them, as we have lately obſerved in the buſineſs of <hi>Glaris,</hi> which ſetting aſide the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152962:46"/>Popes Nuncio's ſtirring in it, would have proved the firſt ſpark of Fire and Diſſention amongſt them, then which he deſires nothing more the better to further his Affairs, and his pretended Reign over <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi> The <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> in thoſe parts are commonly ignorant in their Religion, and being very ſtupid at the bark, and with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, without ever ſearching into Fundamentals; the only name of Catholick actuates, moves, and incites them, without inquiring any farther; but I would have them once for all be undeceived; not ſuffer themſelves to be impoſed upon under the falſe Notion of Catholick: 'Tis a falſe mask under which he lurks the better to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, and bring them to his Leure; thereby to ſet them at odds amongſt themſelves, and having once done that, he will come pouring down upon <hi>Baſil</hi> or <hi>Geneva,</hi> yea, perhaps upon both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Theſe are bars and boundaries which ought to be in a manner Sacred; the <hi>Cantons</hi> ſhould take care that they be never ſuffered to be medled with nor touched; they are to defend them with their Sword in their Hand to the laſt drop of Blood; for this paſſage being clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the diſcord breaking out amongſt them, farewel they, they are undone to all intents and purpoſes, of free <hi>Swiſſe</hi> they'l become <hi>French</hi> Slaves: But now if the generality of the <hi>Swiſſe</hi> be but true to one another, and united, and but ſhew the Uſurper their Teeth, intimating their reſolution of defending what's their own, they may be ſure the <hi>French</hi> King will only bark at a diſtance, on the other hand, if they ſhew no more eagerneſs for theſe two Cities than they did for <hi>Franche Compte:</hi> If they make no ſtouter a reſiſtance than they did there, they will unavoidably poſt on to their total ruine and deſtruction. I know <hi>France</hi> will not bring them under their yoak, but make them tributary. They are now free and abſolute, but let them take heed they ſuffer not their Necks to be brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their yoak; let them call to mind their Ancient Valour, that their Countrey has proved a Sepulchre to the <hi>French,</hi> and that they have forced them to a diſhonourable retreat: <hi>Geneva</hi> is a delicate bit the <hi>French</hi> have a Moneths mind to, ſince ſhe hath appropriated to her ſelf the County of <hi>Gex,</hi> methinks that Republick too lyes very commodiouſly for her purpoſe: They have a long time muttered at the <hi>French</hi> Court, that they meant to reſettle the Biſhop a Savoyard who is nominated by the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> whom he makes to reſide at his Court to make his Right appear: If it were as eaſie for the <hi>French</hi> King to ſettle a Biſhop there as it has been for him to ſettle
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152962:46"/>a Reſident, he would have accompliſht it long ago: Now ſince this Reſident comes in our way, let us ſpeak a word or two by the by concerning his Reſidence. You muſt know he is as neceſſary a Man there, <hi>as the Fifth wheel in a Chariot,</hi> for he is good for nothing but to receive the <hi>Swiſſe</hi> Packet of Letters for the Court, which a Merchant formerly received, ſo that the Sallary, and the Abode of ſuch a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter would be uſeleſs, if there were not ſomething elſe in it. I dare ſay he would have but a poor pittance, had he no other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in but what <hi>France</hi> allows him, and if he had not the beſt part of it from the Clergy: I do remember that the firſt Man that filled this worthy place, was one <hi>Charigni,</hi> a poor pittiful Fellow, whom Mounſieur <hi>De Pompone</hi> had often releaſed out of <hi>Fort L'eveſque</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was committed for Debt, and ſent him thither to get him diſintangled: There he made a Trade of the <hi>Catholick Religion,</hi> for every Sunday and Holy-day was his days of Receipts; every <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyard</hi> that came to Maſs, giving to the Offering Five or Six Souſe, under pretence of maintaining the Church and Prieſt, but rather Mounſieur the Reſident, who beſides kept a kind of an Ordinary where they might dine, the poor Wretch was fain to catch at any thing, for he was no better than a Beads-man living upon Alms at <hi>Paris,</hi> being forced to quit <hi>Province</hi> upon the account of ſome falſe pieces of Five ſous he would have put off, where he was reduc't to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, and all the ſtir he kept at <hi>Geneva</hi> was only to make the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to greeſe his fiſt, and preſent him with ſomething by the by, <hi>as no body knew.</hi> But ſince the time his Secretary has changed his Religion, and ſince he gave his Almoner a box on the Ear, becauſe he ſpoke in behalf of the Proteſtants, upon a Sermon that he and the Reſident came from hearing: I ſay, from that time he hath laid open his folly, he is countermanded, and another of better ſenſe and more diſcretion ſupplies his place. Conſidering the deſign the King has in hand of dividing this City, it ſeems to be in a manner neceſſary at preſent to have a Reſident to acquaint him with all concerns, to find out where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their ſtrength and weakneſs conſiſts; yea, to corrupt ſome Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate or other, as at <hi>Strasbourg;</hi> the enterprize of the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> in the year <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> ought continually to be before their Eyes as a warning; for it is certain, that the <hi>French</hi> King with what amuſement ſoever he may ſeem to divert them; doth but wait a fair opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſpring his Mine, give fire to his Train, and play his old game as he did at <hi>Strasbourg;</hi> ſo that it mightily behoves the Citizens of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152962:47"/>
                  <hi>Geneva</hi> to ſtand upon their guard, and endeavour to diſpoſe their Allies to afford them ſuccour ſo ſoon as ever they find that grand Uſurper to advance; for he is now taking his aim, and ſo well play'd his Cards, that he hath made the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to ſneak and truckle, not daring ſo much as to put his Noſe towards <hi>France:</hi> In times paſt, the Dukes Anceſtors did defend the City of <hi>Geneva</hi> as well as the Inhabitants; they had a great deal more reaſon for it then <hi>France</hi> now a days, upon the account of the pretenſions to it, and the rights the Counts of <hi>Geneva</hi> have yielded up to the Duke of <hi>Savoy. Charles</hi> IV. Proclaimed that Duke Prince of <hi>Geneva,</hi> and of all the Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries thereunto belonging, and they have inherited it till the Year, 1532. But the preſent Duke is ſo far from making any oppoſition againſt <hi>France,</hi> that he would rather deliver up all his Rights and Claims to it, and let himſelf be cullyed out of it under pretence of reinveſting the Biſhop; now although that Prelate ſhould be ſetled, and <hi>France</hi> maſter of it, what courſe would the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> take, if the King would not remit to him? Would he have recourſe to Menaces or Repriſals? If he ſhould do ſo, the King of <hi>France</hi> would jerk him ſoundly, like a Boy, and would make him kiſs the Rod to boot. So that I would not have <hi>Geneva</hi> to flatter her ſelf with the treacherous promiſes of the <hi>French</hi> King, nor yet with the Aſſiſtance; which Policy and Reaſon might oblige the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to ſend them. Let her e'ne rely on her Allies the <hi>Swiſſe Cantons,</hi> upon her own, though ſlender Forces, and upon ſo many <hi>French</hi> Officers who have fled for refuge thither, who will be ſure upon the firſt news of it, to run to her aſſiſtance, or otherwiſe they muſt have loſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe, and all ſentiments of Honour and Thankfulneſs. Again, if ſo be the Emperour make his Peace with the <hi>Turk,</hi> he muſt ſend for the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> to help him, who is a great Captain, and even laden with Victorious Lawrels, whoſe very name will make <hi>France</hi> quake. I, and he may ſerve him for a inlet whereat to enter into his Dutchy of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> where his Subjects quite ſpent with the Tyrannical Dominion of <hi>France,</hi> expect him as their <hi>Moſes</hi> and deliverer.</p>
               <p>The King is a Lyon in a Foxes Skin, he is not ſo formidable as men believe him; his only end is to make himſelf be feared, and he obtains his deſire by threatnings; but ſhake off this panick fear, look upon <hi>France</hi> nearer, mind her ſoberly and ſeriouſly, conſider the continual running away of her Inhabitants, the puniſhment and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152962:47"/>impriſonment of another part of them, is as ſo much Bloud flowing from her Veins, which by little and little weaken her. Add hereto the juſt complaints of the Catholicks, the decreaſe of her Revenues, and what is worſt of all for her, the death and the going away of ſo many Generals within theſe few years, and ſo ſuddenly one after another, doth ſhe not ſeem to behold that Scene Heaven hath contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on purpoſe to humble her, for indeed ſhe is at a lower ebb then one would imagine: I'll engage ſhe is as ſick as her King, and that they be both ſmitten to the heart.</p>
               <p>The firſt Enemy that ſets upon her will not be long alone, he will be ſoon ſeconded; but it will be juſt as in the Fable of the Counſel of Rats, who conſulted together to go hang a Bell at the Cats neck their ſworn Enemy, but not one of them durſt venture to do it firſt. Who would ever have ſaid the Pope would have contributed his aſſiſtance to the Union of the <hi>Switzers?</hi> Yet 'tis true he did ſo, as we may have obſerved in the buſineſs of <hi>Glaris,</hi> which I have above recited: Nay his <hi>Nuncio</hi> is very intent, at his leiſure hours, to open the eyes of the Catholick <hi>Cantons;</hi> for thoſe ſilly people, provided the King tell them of intending to re-eſtabliſh a Biſhop, 'tis enough for them, that's all they care for, but they are not ſenſible of what is behind the Hill, that the grand Uſurper lyes hid under the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Mitre.</p>
               <p>I have but one Admonition more to give the Right Honourable <hi>Cantons</hi> of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> that is to ſay, the King hath no reſpect nor good will towards them. He takes them for Scaffolds to be made uſe of when need requires, and when that is over, he looks upon them as no body. I deſire no other proof of what I ſay, then what of a freſh date happened to the Ambaſſador, which the <hi>Cantons</hi> not long ſince ſent to the <hi>French</hi> King: After he had wrangled with them about their Commiſſion not being in general Terms, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to refuſe them Audience; well, this difficulty once removed by a ſecond Commiſſion diſpatched to them, they were e'ne fain to go away as they came, without ſo much as ſeeing the King, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining one only Audience. This is the greateſt undervaluing, and moſt ſenſible affront that ever Free-born men had given; and if the <hi>Cantons</hi> paſs by this, and don't ſhew their juſt Reſentments of it, they'l be deſpiſed by all the Princes of <hi>Europe;</hi> and it will not be the laſt ill turn of this nature that will befall. But that I may fully certifie you of the truth of what I here deliver, ſee here word for
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152962:48"/>word the Harangue, or rather Complement, theſe Gentlemen paſt upon Mounſieur <hi>Colbert Croiſſi</hi> Miniſter of the Foreign Affairs at their departure.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes"> Sir, Our Lords and Superiours ſending us hither to do what in us lyes, and make uſe of all importunities to endeavour to win the Kings affection, to the end he might be inclined to uphold the City of <hi>Geneva</hi> their Allie, in the poſſeſſion of what they have hitherto been above One Hundred and Eighty Years grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Authentick Treaties.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But his Majeſty being reſolved to commit to his Parliament of <hi>Dijon,</hi> a buſineſs which is plainly acknowledged for an affair of State, which depends upon Treaties of Peace, Covenants and Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances; the which ſaid Parliament our Superiours will never acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as juſt, no, nor give their Allies, the Citts of <hi>Geneva,</hi> counſel to yield to their Treaty, which is theirs alſo. Moreover his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty giving us to underſtand by your Excellency, that he would no more then you confer with us touching this matter; and becauſe we are afraid that a longer ſtay here might be as unwelcome as our coming; we could not do better then withdraw home again to make a faithful report of what hath paſt to our Lords and Superiours.</p>
               <p>We are come to take our leaves of your Excellency, and to give you many thanks for the patience you have had in ſeveral Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, beſeeching you that in purſuance of the reiterated Orders we have had given us in behalf of our Lords and Superiours, who notwithſtanding they be much troubled at the bad ſucceſs of this Embaſſy (ſeeing they take more into conſideration the proſecution of 25 Canons, then the fidelity of many thouſands of the beſt and moſt ſtedfaſt Allies of that Crown, who have ſhed their Blood, and ſacrificed ſo many brave men, for the ſervice, grandeur, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of that State) yet that nevertheleſs they will ſtand to their Treaty of Peace and Allyance, in the hopes they have always enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and do ſtill entertain, that his Majeſty, (to whom with the Royal Family they wiſh all happineſs) will on his part be reſponſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. As for our part in particular, though we have not had the happineſs to ſee his Majeſty, yet we cannot choſe but wiſh him all Perſonal Health, and do aſſure your Excellency, of the eſteem and high value we put, and all ways ſhall, upon your deſerts and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable vertue, proteſting to you, that we are more particularly your moſt humble Servant.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:152962:48"/>
               <p>After ſuch a baſe affront, who would not undervallue ſuch Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours the Repreſentatives, and their Superiours alſo, who durſt preſent them with a Golden Chain of 500 Crowns value? One would think they had an hand in it, and that they were covetous of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Preſents: If an Embaſſadour after taking ſuch an affront ſhould have accepted it, he would have deſerved to be hanged with that Golden Coller. By the refuſal of Audience you may well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what <hi>France</hi> is made of, and its deſigns: Whoever heard or ſaw a free and abſolute Republique referr'd to a Parliament under his Authority, as the King refers <hi>Geneva</hi> to the Parliament at <hi>Dijon;</hi> it would have been more legal and juſt to have refer'd them to the Parliament at <hi>Turin.</hi> Now behold the equity of this great King, who would always be both Judge and Party in his own Cauſe, who would make all <hi>Europe</hi> depend on his Judges; ſome upon thoſe of <hi>Metz,</hi> others on thoſe of <hi>Dijon</hi> and <hi>Aix</hi> in <hi>Provence,</hi> as he forces the people of <hi>Orange</hi> to do; but we hope thoſe of <hi>Geneva</hi> will not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to thoſe unjuſt Judges; and ſuppoſing they do, they will not miſs loſing their Cauſe, and after that, they will make a new pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion upon them, till they have fettered them, and loſing their City and Liberty, they become the ſlaves of <hi>France;</hi> a Victim offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up to the Jeſuit, and the Conqueſt of <hi>Lewis</hi> the great, and it is odds, but that will be ſo indeed if they don't look about them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and prepare themſelves for its coming upon them; for he'l come and give them a viſit, as he did the <hi>Genoueſes.</hi> Let them not flatter themſelves with the contrary, when he ſhall make them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to ſacrifice themſelves for their Liberty, rather then to a Prince who would be their <hi>Antiochus,</hi> their bloody Maſter, and would ſnatch the Children from their Mothers embraces to deliver them into the hands of the Jeſuits; make them forſake Relations, Religion, and all duty of Chriſtians, and refuſing to obey this ambition, would hale them to the Scaffold, and throw their Carcaſſes to dogs; nay, if ſo be they ſhould deal more gently with them, it would be only to make them bear company with his own Subjects in Dungeons, in the Gallies, and in the <hi>Weſt-Indies.</hi> Now take notice of this Spirit of <hi>France,</hi> and beware of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:152962:49"/>
               <head>That <hi>Lewis XIV.</hi> is no good Chriſtian.</head>
               <p>I Shall finiſh this Treatiſe in demonſtrating that this King is no good Chriſtian, that it is but a cloak for his Knavery, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to play faſt and looſe, the better to bring about his ambitious deſigns, that albeit he makes a great clutter with the title of moſt Chriſtian King at <hi>Rome,</hi> yet we find him to be nothing leſs: All who are baptized are not Chriſtians, for then we might reckon <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate and <hi>Arrius</hi> to be ſuch, whom men look upon as Apoſtates and <hi>Antichriſts.</hi> I am perſwaded the Marquiſs <hi>de Monteſpan</hi> will juſtifie what I ſay. I cannot think that Prince worthy the name of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian who covets his Neighbours Wife; nay before all the World takes her from her Husband, makes uſe of her, and begets Children of her, whom he would fain get declared natural, never before <hi>Lewis</hi> his time practiced in <hi>France:</hi> He cannot aſſume the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian who makes little Conſcience to break the moſt ſolemn Oaths and Engagements made at the Communion, as he did at the Peace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded at the <hi>Perinees,</hi> upon his Marriage with the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain.</hi> And then the Oath taken at his Coronation, to obſerve the Edicts of pacification, are they not dayly violated and retracted upon every frivolous pretence? Good Chriſtians are ſuch who live up to thoſe Vows they have made, even to very Infidels.</p>
               <p>The Marquiſs <hi>de Laverdin</hi> making his publick entrance into <hi>Rome,</hi> did chooſe rather to do it like a Fox than a Lyon, (as ſince it appears) without ever determining any thing poſitively concerning it, when they demanded him to explain himſelf before he made his entrance; ſo that engaging himſelf neither <hi>pro</hi> nor <hi>con,</hi> it will always be time enough, and ſeaſonable to make his Maſters will to ſtand him in ſtead, as we ſhall ſee hereafter, when the <hi>Provencal</hi> Fleet ſhall be before <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vita Vechia,</hi> and other Ports of the Popes Dominion; beſides that, it was convenient to carry it fair to obtain the Bull for the Cardinal of <hi>Furſtenburg,</hi> whom <hi>France</hi> was aſſured would be nominated to the Coadjutorſhip of <hi>Cologn;</hi> the Dean and Chapter, as 'tis credibly given out, fingered the Kings Money; to that in effect it was regiſtred and their Votes ſold, ſo that it was not poſſible to go back with their word. When the Marquiſs <hi>de Lavardin</hi> entred <hi>Rome,</hi> the buſineſs
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152962:49"/>was as good as done, and the King made ſure of it, but he found himſelf miſtaken, as to the Bull, for he believed the Pope, who is wiſe and good natured enough of himſelf, not loving noiſe, would yield at the Embaſſadors arrival, that the Spiritual would give place to the Temporal; but he was deceived in his account, meeting with ſuch ſtiffneſs and vigour in an old man, which it may be one durſt not have hoped for in a young man. In the mean time behold the Marquiſs <hi>de Lavardin</hi> keeping watch and ward night and day, and that round about the Palace of <hi>Ferneſe,</hi> juſt as if it were a Fort ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with enemies, before the Pope and the Conclave of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals Noſes: By all theſe riots and indignities done to the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perſon of the Church, Vicar of Chriſt, and St. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor, is nothing in compariſon to that which <hi>Talon</hi> the Kings Advocate hath belched forth againſt his Holineſs, and the Cardinals his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, accuſing the former to be a favourer of Hereſie, Janſeniſme, and of Quietiſts, and a thouſand other impertinences, which is to be ſeen more at large in the demand of the aboveſaid <hi>Talon</hi> to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Paris,</hi> and by the Embaſſadors proteſtation publickly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed at <hi>Rome,</hi> the expreſſions therein are ſcandalous, that they might deſervedly procure the fire for a private perſon; but when one hath the power in his own hand, he thinks he may Lawfully ſay and do whatſoever likes him: But the Pope who is grave and wiſe will let him go on, yea peradventure his great modeſty and prudent beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour may make the King come to himſelf again, and acknowledge the wrong, and that the Pope is Maſter at home in his own Houſe, and may be able to diſannul and take away the Franchiſes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors quarters, when he ſhall ſee it convenient for the repoſe of his People, and his own Conſcience.</p>
               <p>It is not his frequenting Maſs which is a Characteriſtical mark of being a Chriſtian, or for being kind to the Jeſuits; for fear awes Princes ſometimes to make much of Jeſuits, and ſhew much reſpect to them. <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. was not free from this fear, when he would have reſtored them in <hi>France;</hi> for when the Duke of <hi>Sully</hi> adviſed him to the contrary, he ſtarted up and replyed, <hi>ſecure me my Life then;</hi> for 'twas more then probable, that thoſe who ſued for their return had aſſured the King, that if he did not do it he would be in immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger of being Murthered: When Life is at ſtake what will not a man do to ſave it? Who can tell but theſe good Fathers have told the King now Reigning, if in caſe he did not root out all the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152962:50"/>
                  <hi>Huguenots</hi> out of his Dominions, this muſt come in alwayes, <hi>ad majorem Dei Gloriam,</hi> that he would endanger his Life.</p>
               <p>What ſign of a Chriſtian was there in the King when he made a League with <hi>Cromwel</hi> to fall upon the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> and to baniſh <hi>Charles</hi> II. from his Kingdom, who was rightful Succeſſor to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and a good Catholick in his heart, although af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards out of Policy he was fain to appear otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Again, what ſign of Chriſtianity doth there appear in a Prince who aſſiſts Count <hi>Tekely</hi> in league with the <hi>Turks</hi> againſt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour? A King who forbids all Biſhops and Curats throughout his Dominion to cauſe <hi>Te Deum</hi> to be ſung for the Victories of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians obtained over the <hi>Turks,</hi> who impedes by force of <hi>Lewiſſes</hi> the progreſs of the King of <hi>Polands</hi> Forces againſt the ſame <hi>Turks,</hi> that they may have the opportunity to employ all the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Forces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Emperour, thereby to make him abandon what he hath got at the dear rate of ſo much Chriſtian blood.</p>
               <p>What Chriſtianity do you obſerve in the Kings proceeding at the Cities of <hi>Genoua</hi> and <hi>Orange,</hi> where he hath no right at all: So that by all that I have alledged, all theſe Titles of moſt Chriſtian and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Zeal the King is ſo much taken with, and affects, is only a deceitful mask of hypocriſie to lull the Catholick Princes aſleep, the better to play his game, and make himſelf Maſter of them one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another. Although the King of <hi>England</hi> would hinder him, as being the only man that could beſt do it, he would endeavour to cauſe an inſurrection of the Church of <hi>England</hi> men againſt him, he would ſend them Money and Officers as he did to <hi>Cromwel;</hi> ſo that one may ſay of the <hi>French</hi> King that he becomes all things to all men, when his intereſt is at ſtake: He enters into Covenant with <hi>Turk</hi> or <hi>Hugue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, Pagans</hi> or <hi>Infidels,</hi> againſt Catholicks themſelves, if it be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for promoting his greatneſs, and to attain to the Monarchy of all <hi>Europe.</hi> And for a concluſion this is the Kings Religion, and your Wit and Policy of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
